<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>One and forty divine odes Englished set to King Davids princely harpe. By S.P.L.</title>
            <author>Brazil. Ministério do Interior. Secretaria de Planejamento.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72505</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15110</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123169</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899104</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899104</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150662</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72505)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150662)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1966:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>One and forty divine odes Englished set to King Davids princely harpe. By S.P.L.</title>
                  <author>Brazil. Ministério do Interior. Secretaria de Planejamento.</author>
                  <author>Sempill, James, Sir, 1566-1625, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 39, [3], 41-94 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by M[iles] F[lesher and Robert Young for Richard Moore],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Sir James Sempill.</note>
                  <note>With an additional title page: An assay, or Buchanan his paraphrase on the first twentie Psalmes of Dauid translated. London, printed by R[obert]. Y[oung]. for Richard Moore in St. Dunstones Church-yard in Fleetstreet. 1627.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Flesher's and Young's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, San Marino, California.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150662:1"/>
            <p>One and forty DIVINE ODES ENGLISHED, SET TO KING DAVIDS Princely Harpe.</p>
            <p>By <hi>S. P. L.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> 1627.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150662:2"/>
            <p>AN ASSAY, OR BVCHANAN HIS PARAPHRASE ON THE FIRST twentie Pſalmes of DAVID TRANSLATED</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>R. Y.</hi> for <hi>Richard Moore</hi> in St. Dunſtones Church-yard in Fleetſtreet. 1627.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150662:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150662:3"/>
            <head>TO THE KING His moſt excellent MAIESTIE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>
                  </hi> King put in a baſer weeede,</l>
               <l>And brought vnto your Princely view,</l>
               <l>Some man that may miſdeem the deed,</l>
               <l>And doubt ſome danger to enſue,</l>
               <l>Will ſay that no diſguiſe is good</l>
               <l>For Kings, or for the Royall blood.</l>
               <l>But, Sir, by bleſſed proofe we finde</l>
               <l>Cloathes change the man, but not the minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With Him Heau'ns darling then aduiſe,</l>
               <l>Who, though diſguis'd, will not diſguiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VRANIA to the King.</head>
               <l>Deſcended firſt of Kingly blood,</l>
               <l>Bequeath'd ſince to your royall race,</l>
               <l>More humbly-bold in hope I ſtood</l>
               <l>Of entertainment with your Grace.</l>
               <l>And though diſroab'd by this am knowne,</l>
               <l>I ſing <hi>Iehouahs</hi> name alone.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:150662:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150662:4"/>
            <div n="1" type="ode">
               <head>PSALM I.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Bleſſed He, whom from the ſacred way</l>
                  <l>Lewd mens contagion hath not ſwai'd aſide,</l>
                  <l>Nor errors paths hath trod, nor made his ſtay</l>
                  <l>In ſcorners trade, ſet in their chaire of pride:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 But who to th' track of better life enur'd,</l>
                  <l>Doth on Gods Law his time, and ſpirits ſpend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Hee like a tree which ſunne and winde endur'd,</l>
                  <l>Low on a banke ſet by the ſtreames, ſhall ſend</l>
                  <l>His branches wide, which in abundance yeeld,</l>
                  <l>And bleſſe the Planter with faire fruit, nor ſhowes</l>
                  <l>His flowring bloomes but to adorne the field,</l>
                  <l>And mocke the Maſter while it fruitleſſe growes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 It fares not ſo with them, who void of grace,</l>
                  <l>Like out-lawes ſleight the Heauens, they ſoon ſhall flie</l>
                  <l>As duſt, which with the whirle-wind leaues his place,</l>
                  <l>And mounting capers in the vaulted skie,</l>
                  <l>As if the winde did take a ſport to ſee</l>
                  <l>It dancing there, and making many a round.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 But when the Iudge of right ſhall ſeated be</l>
                  <l>On a faire cloud, his head with glory crown'd,</l>
                  <l>And holds his Scepter in his royall hand</l>
                  <l>To iudge the world of ſinne; then ſhall not proud,</l>
                  <l>Iniquity in publick preſence ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhew her face where iuſt men are allow'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:150662:5"/>
                  <l n="6">6 For Heauens great King knowes their vnſpotted way,</l>
                  <l>Viewes all their hearts, and all enclos'd therin,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe that in blinde errors by-paths ſtray,</l>
                  <l>Shall periſh with their crooked waies of ſinne.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. II.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHy doe the Nations rage, and raiſe the cry,</l>
                  <l>And headlong run in a tumultuous fright?</l>
                  <l>Their threats why dart the people at the skie?</l>
                  <l>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> With tyrants why conſpire the men of might?</l>
                  <l>All 'gainſt the Lord, and his Anointed plot,</l>
                  <l>When all in vaine their proiects proſper not.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Why burſt we not couragiouſly, they ſay,</l>
                  <l>And free vs from their bonds that yoke our necks?</l>
                  <l>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> But God in Heauen, who all on earth doth ſway,</l>
                  <l>Laughs at their pride, and their vain threatning checks.</l>
                  <l>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Then wretched them He in his rage wil cal,</l>
                  <l>And marre their plots when fury flames his gall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> I will, ſaith He, encircle with a crowne</l>
                  <l>My ſacred King, that plac'd on Sion hill,</l>
                  <l>He may giue Law, inueſted with renowne,</l>
                  <l>And through the world ſpread wide my royall will;</l>
                  <l>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Thou art my Son (thus ſaid the Lord to me)</l>
                  <l>Of Heau'nly ſeed this day begat I thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Aske Thou, and haue in tenure of free-hold,</l>
                  <l>As my ſole Heire, what Earth and Sea containe;</l>
                  <l>That what the Heauens in their wide armes infold,</l>
                  <l>May all be thine, and Thou as Monarch raigne:</l>
                  <l>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> And with an iron Scepter rule, and bray</l>
                  <l>Th'inſulting proud, as Pipkins made of clay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> But you, who haue the honour to diſcerne,</l>
                  <l>And iudge the Nations by the doome of Law,</l>
                  <l>Diſpell the clouds of error, while you learne</l>
                  <l>Truth from aboue, and ſerue the Lord in awe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:150662:5"/>And you, Earth's gods, who rule with ſou'raign might,</l>
                  <l>Be wiſe your ſelues, &amp; ſee the reſt do right.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Serue God with feare, and finding ſweet content,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ioyne with your ioy that awe to him is due,</l>
                  <l>That you may kiſſe his Son whom He hath ſent,</l>
                  <l>Leſt whilſt you ſtray rage and reuenge purſue.</l>
                  <l>Soon, when iuſt wrath his flames 'gainſt ſin ſhall throw,</l>
                  <l>How happy they who hope in him, you'l know.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. III.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AH what a rout, viewd either by the poll</l>
                  <l>Or by the bulk, vexe me with deadly hate!</l>
                  <l>How many troupes doe their lewd names enroll,</l>
                  <l>Conſpiring all againſt my life, and ſtate!</l>
                  <l>Whilſt they dare ſay, No hopes at all remaine <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>In God for him; He lookes for help in vaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When yet in combate often my ſoule bleedes,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>And thou me ſhield'ſt that no force beates me down,</l>
                  <l>When all my praiſe, and worth from thee proceedes,</l>
                  <l>When thou with glory do'ſt my temples crowne;</l>
                  <l>When in the night I doe thy grace recount,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>And God, my God, heares from his holy Mount,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then cleere from cares I lye, and take my reſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>And riſe againe as ſafe, and free from feare;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt He doth guard, no fright inuades my breaſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though endleſſe troupes of armed foes be neere:</l>
                  <l>When all fell Nations bandy againſt me,</l>
                  <l>Thou, Lord, wilt leade the point, to ſet me free;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And thou wilt breake the iaw-bones of my foes,</l>
                  <l>And daſh their teeth out with thine angry fiſt,</l>
                  <l>But thou, the hope of all, our ſafe repoſe,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Whilſt thou alone do'ſt all miſhaps reſiſt)</l>
                  <l>Thy people in thine armes of loue embrace,</l>
                  <l>And guard them with thy wonted hand of grace.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="ode">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:150662:6"/>
               <head>PSAL. IIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHo mad'ſt, and rul'ſt aboue, below,</l>
                  <l>Angells, and gods of mortall kinde</l>
                  <l>And conſcious of my thoughts do'ſt know</l>
                  <l>The cleerer current of my minde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who in a ſafe and ſpacious plaine,</l>
                  <l>(When I in ſtraights doe ſue for aide)</l>
                  <l>Do'ſt leade me forth ſet free againe,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt counſell failes, my ſelfe vnſtaid,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Propitious with thine eare of grace,</l>
                  <l>Heare calmly what I iuſtly vow,</l>
                  <l>Giue way and welcome to my caſe</l>
                  <l>Whom hatefull ſpight beleaguers now.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 O mindes of men enuolu'd in vaine,</l>
                  <l>And idle ſhadowes that deceiue,</l>
                  <l>Why will you not haue me to raigne,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt you of reſt your ſelues bereaue?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 Beleeue at length, I tell you true,</l>
                  <l>Whom God hath choſe from all the reſt,</l>
                  <l>And grac'd him more than was his due,</l>
                  <l>No man can hurt whom he hath bleſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Lord did heare me when I cri'd,</l>
                  <l>And laid before him my ſad caſe,</l>
                  <l>Nor helpe I crau'd, hath he deni'd,</l>
                  <l>Or hath ſhut vp his gate of grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 Then wretched you, Gods awefull might</l>
                  <l>Recount at length, and ceaſe to ſinne,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150662:6"/>And caſt in ſilent bed at night</l>
                  <l>The day, and all that paſt therein.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 'Tis not the entrals of a beaſt</l>
                  <l>Wherein the Lord doth liking finde,</l>
                  <l>A faithfull heart he makes his feaſt,</l>
                  <l>And beſt accepts a guiltleſſe minde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If this thou to the Altar bring,</l>
                  <l>And offer it with due regard,</l>
                  <l>If Truth be true, from Heauens great King,</l>
                  <l>Thou maiſt expect a rich reward.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 The moſt of men growne out of kinde,</l>
                  <l>Affect proud wealth which they adore;</l>
                  <l n="8">8 But when thy beames on me haue ſhin'd</l>
                  <l>With ſmiling looks, I ſeek no more.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let others loade their barnes with corne,</l>
                  <l>And with ſweet wine their cellars fill,</l>
                  <l>With gold cramm'd vp in plenties horne</l>
                  <l>Let them haue all they wiſh, or will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 But free from cares I'le take my reſt,</l>
                  <l>And with ſweet ſleepes will ſpend the night,</l>
                  <l>With hope from Heauen thou ſteelſt my breaſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſhieldſt me ſafe, Lord, with thy might.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. V.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHoſe ſupreme power o're all extends</l>
                  <l>Benignely, Lord, my praiers heare,</l>
                  <l>And with a calme and facile eare</l>
                  <l>Receiue the plaines which ſorrow ſends.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:150662:7"/>
                  <l n="2">2 When loud I call, attentiue ſee</l>
                  <l>How my full vaines diſtend my heart,</l>
                  <l>My God and King alone thou art,</l>
                  <l>And in diſtreſſe I ſerue but thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Lord, heare me when I early cry,</l>
                  <l>For while pure vowes cheere hopes within,</l>
                  <l>I'le call on thee ere beames begin</l>
                  <l>To ſparkle from the Suns bright eie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 Thou, God, who lou'ſt a pious minde,</l>
                  <l>And hat'ſt the filth of impious rites,</l>
                  <l>Let him whoſe ſoule in ſin delights,</l>
                  <l>Hopeleſſe of thee no fauour finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 Arm'd wrong flies from thy dreadfull ſight,</l>
                  <l n="6">6 Who art a foe to bloud, and fraud,</l>
                  <l>The glozing tongue that doth applaud</l>
                  <l>Foule falſhood, thou wilt cut out quite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 Since on thy grace I, Lord, relie,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſacred gates will I draw neere,</l>
                  <l>And to thy Temple goe with feare,</l>
                  <l>And ſend pure vowes to thee on high.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 That I my foese ſlinets may finde,</l>
                  <l>Thou, God of Right, thy light diſplay,</l>
                  <l>And in a darke and doubtfull way</l>
                  <l>Direct my ſteps, which elſe are blinde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 Truth ſhuns the lips of my proud foes,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt filth and fraud keep th' inner roomes,</l>
                  <l>Their throates ſmell worſe than rotten toombes,</l>
                  <l>Their tongues with honied poiſon gloze,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:150662:7"/>
                  <l>And inly minde cloſely to wound.</l>
                  <l n="10">10 O God, the ſource whence all things ſpring,</l>
                  <l>Deſtroy the wicked Nation, bring</l>
                  <l>Their drifts to naught, and who doſt found</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And foſter all, confound the vaine</l>
                  <l>And idle plots they vndertake,</l>
                  <l>Quite roote them out who thee forſake,</l>
                  <l>And due to ſin feele they the paine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 But by thy grace, Lord, guarded ſtill</l>
                  <l>Let them be glad who fixe on thee</l>
                  <l>Their hopes alone, and feareleſſe free</l>
                  <l>Adore thy Name, and euer will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 Pure mindes to Heauen which homage yeeld,</l>
                  <l>Thou cheer'ſt with treaſures from thy ſtore,</l>
                  <l>And when refreſh'd, they need no more,</l>
                  <l>Thy fauour ſhades them like a ſhield.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. VI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHilſt anger boiles, and rage inflames thy gall,</l>
                  <l>Correct me not, though ſin for vengeance call;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt fury burnes, and runs a ſwifter pace</l>
                  <l>To bring fell plagues on body, ſoule, and all,</l>
                  <l>Spare, ſpare me, Lord, whom griefe doth ſo appall,</l>
                  <l>Lay iuſtice by, and vſe thy hand of grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My force is ſpent, my bones the bodies ſtay,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aile, ſince their nerues are loos'd where vigour lay,</l>
                  <l n="3">3 And care doth vexe my troubled ſpirit ſore.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow long wilt thou neglect, and keep away,</l>
                  <l>And leaue me on the rack, vext night, and day?</l>
                  <l>Come now, and me from deaths fell iawes reſtore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:150662:8"/>
                  <l n="5">5 When he hath once ceaz'd with his griping paw,</l>
                  <l>Not leauing one poore puffe of breath to draw,</l>
                  <l>Who thinkes on thee? Ah no, it it too late,</l>
                  <l>Wrapt vp in mold, made ſubiect to deaths law,</l>
                  <l>(Where men are like thoſe births that no Sun ſaw)</l>
                  <l>Who there thy Name ſhall ſing, or praiſe relate?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 When in the night my grieued ſoule agaſt,</l>
                  <l>Breathes forth deepe ſighes, as if ſhe breath'd her laſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>With weeping eies I waſh my mournefull bed,</l>
                  <l>That all the cloathes which on my couch are caſt</l>
                  <l>Are wet with teares, which trickle downe ſo faſt</l>
                  <l>As if a ſhower of raine powr'd from my head.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 My fight, once quick, her vertue now hath ſpent</l>
                  <l>With gripes of griefe, and pining diſcontent.</l>
                  <l>The liuely vigour of my limmes is gone</l>
                  <l>Whilſt that my foes their wiles applauding went,</l>
                  <l>And for their plots which nought but miſchief men</l>
                  <l>In my freſh checkes now ruddy hue is none.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 The curſed crue, Ah you, that ſo delight</l>
                  <l>In graceleſſe acts, hence, hence now take your flight,</l>
                  <l>Caſt off the hopes which you conceiu'd in vaine</l>
                  <l n="9">9 God calmely heard the roarings of my ſpri't,</l>
                  <l>And though you grieue and enuy at the ſight,</l>
                  <l>He heard my vowes and rais'd me vp againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 Let ſodaine ſhame mine enemies diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>The guilty bluſh let it confound their face,</l>
                  <l>Let infamy which them to horror driues,</l>
                  <l>Make pale their lookes to ſhew their dolefull caſe,</l>
                  <l>And in their hearts let tort'ring griefe take place,</l>
                  <l>Who fled, and left me like baſe fugitiues.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="ode">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:150662:8"/>
               <head>PSAL. VII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SInce I in thee my ſafties hope haue plac'd,</l>
                  <l>(Great Keeper of all things in this our All)</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n their fell iawes who alwaies me diſgrac'd,</l>
                  <l>Lord, let not thou, let not thy ſeruant fall;</l>
                  <l>Like ſauage beaſts more like than ciuill men,</l>
                  <l>They plot my death, deuiſing how, and when.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If none doe come and take my cauſe in hand,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s a fierce Lion teares the harmleſſe Sheepe,</l>
                  <l>Who at firſt fight affrighted doe disband,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o my fell foe (who wakes whilſt others ſleepe)</l>
                  <l>Will rend my limmes, whoſe thirſt of blood is ſu<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>He ſheds, if guiltleſſe, he cares not how much.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If he accus'd whoſe faith had taineleſſe ſtood,</l>
                  <l>Nor lying lips had warp'd and wou'n falſe crimes;</l>
                  <l>If I haue wrought them ill, who meant but good,</l>
                  <l>Or ſpar'd not thoſe who harm'd me many times,</l>
                  <l n="5">5 Me let my foe purſue, and ouertake;</l>
                  <l>And taken, foile, and foild, his foot-ball make,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd let him tread, and trample in the mire</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y Diadem, the enſigne of my pride:</l>
                  <l>But, Lord, ariſe, let rage and lewd deſire</l>
                  <l>Of my proud foes (thy mercy laid aſide)</l>
                  <l>Incenſe thee to iuſt ire, riſe, Lord, and pay</l>
                  <l>Thy vowd reuenge to thoſe who Truth betray.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ariſe, and let thy ſacred Maieſty</l>
                  <l>His beames diſplay, and all parts ouerſpread,</l>
                  <l>And let all people to their Parlies hie,</l>
                  <l>And thee proclaime their fire and ſupreme Head.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:150662:9"/>Thou, whoſe ſtrong hand holds all the Scepters her<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l n="8">8 And vindicates the ſins done eu'ry where,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Reuenge my wrong, if rightly I implore</l>
                  <l>With hallow'd mouth, and mind, plagues on my fo<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l n="9">9 O thou iuſt Iudge, who knows our thoughts befo<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>We ſpeake or thinke, whoſe eie doth all diſcloſe,</l>
                  <l>Batter, and bruiſe lewd mens all-daring luſt,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt grace ſupports and animates the iuſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 I ſcorne all foes if God be on my ſide,</l>
                  <l n="11">11 Who takes delight, where Candor takes her ſea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>In mindes that haue nor welts, nor guards of pride,</l>
                  <l>And godly men protects when dangers threate,</l>
                  <l>And not by fits, but by a fixt decree</l>
                  <l>Menaceth death to thoſe that impious be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 If ſtiffe my foe ſtands in his vaine pretence,</l>
                  <l n="13">13 Then God ſoone drawes his ſword, he bends hi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> bow</l>
                  <l>He ſnatcheth vp his dart of more offence,</l>
                  <l>Which, where it lights doth giue a dang'rous blow;</l>
                  <l>He whets his ſhafts, with fury firy red,</l>
                  <l>That carries death on the ſharp-pointed head.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="14">14 Behold who great with ſin beings miſchief forth</l>
                  <l>And plots againſt my guiltleſſe ſoule deſign'd,</l>
                  <l>He brought to light things that were little worth,</l>
                  <l>Like fancies which affright a ſleeping mind,</l>
                  <l n="15">15 He digg'd a pit, and cloſely laide his gin,</l>
                  <l>But miſſing me, himſelfe was caught therein.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="16">16 On his owne head ſhall all his follies fall,</l>
                  <l>And where they heed ſhall all his miſchiefes light,</l>
                  <l n="17">17 Then free from feare, and enuies bitter gall</l>
                  <l>I'le ſing of thee, and thine impartiall right</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:150662:9"/>And glorious name. O thou all-ruling Lord,</l>
                  <l>With cheerfull mind I will thy praiſe record.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. VIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FAther, and Foſtrer of mankind,</l>
                  <l>How haue the raies of thy renowne</l>
                  <l>Aſtoniſh'd all, on whom haue ſhin'd</l>
                  <l>The beames which Heauens great light darts down?</l>
                  <l>Thy greatneſſe hath ſurmounted far</l>
                  <l>The Spheares, where ſtars bright gliſtring ar,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 How thou do'ſt rule the world with care,</l>
                  <l>The infant age, yet ſucking tells,</l>
                  <l>That thou maiſt ſtop the mouthes that dare</l>
                  <l>Barke at thy power, which ſo excells.</l>
                  <l>Such mouthes at thee as poiſon ſpue,</l>
                  <l>And thirſt for bloud which they purſue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 When I behold the Heauens ſo cleere</l>
                  <l>With pureſt light made by thine hand,</l>
                  <l>When Moone, and Stars ſo bright appeare,</l>
                  <l>And all by thee created ſtand,</l>
                  <l n="4">4 Ah, what is man in life, or lim</l>
                  <l>Thinke I, that thus thou mindeſt him?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What is his ſtock, his of-ſpring what,</l>
                  <l>To whom thou daign'ſt ſuch honour, ſuch</l>
                  <l>A gracefull eye of fauour, that</l>
                  <l n="5">5 Hee's like a God, the oddes not much?</l>
                  <l n="6">6 Thou mad'ſt him Prince, to vndergoe</l>
                  <l>The rule of all thou mad'ſt below.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of all that breathes, by right of birth,</l>
                  <l>Thou mad'ſt him maſter of their wills,</l>
                  <l n="7">7 The horn'd, and the fleec'd flocks on earth,</l>
                  <l>And all that feedes on plaines and hills,</l>
                  <l n="8">
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:150662:10"/>8 Or what with wings or ſinns diuide</l>
                  <l>The aire and Sea, He tames their pride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 Father, and foſtrer of mankind,</l>
                  <l>How haue the raies of thy renowne</l>
                  <l>Aſtoniſh'd all, on whom haue ſhin'd</l>
                  <l>The beames which Heauens great light darts down?</l>
                  <l>Whoſe throne is Heauen, whoſe foot-ſtoole Earth,</l>
                  <l>Protect thine one of nobleſt birth.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. IX.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>OF thee I ſing, great Guardian of all things,</l>
                  <l>To thee my heart her duties tribute paies,</l>
                  <l>Thy wonders to our ſeed that after ſprings</l>
                  <l>I will declare, and thence thy glory raiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Safe guided by thy hand I'le nothing feare,</l>
                  <l>But cheerfull notes will ſing with cheerfull mind,</l>
                  <l>And will thee praiſe, who ſupreme rule do'ſt beare,</l>
                  <l>Chiefe Iuſtice of the Heau'ns, and heau'nly kind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 My prouder foe, who, without counſell led,</l>
                  <l>Conceiu'd vain hopes, hath turn'd, and took his flight,</l>
                  <l>And thy right-hand purſuing whilſt he fled,</l>
                  <l>With more than humane force hath foil'd him quite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 My greedy foes wide yawning for my bloud,</l>
                  <l>Thy wreakfull rage confounds, and rends their iawes;</l>
                  <l>Thine aide releeu'd while guilty-like I ſtood,</l>
                  <l>And from thy Throne thy doome did end my cauſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 Thou tam'ſt the fury of the ſauage rout,</l>
                  <l>Thy matchleſſe might did ſo my foes diſpell,</l>
                  <l>As in the roules of Fame they were left out,</l>
                  <l>That none their names in after-age ſhould tell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:150662:10"/>
                  <l n="6">6 Lo, to what end come all theſe ſwelling threats?</l>
                  <l>Lo him that townes would leuell, and lay plaine,</l>
                  <l>That where in former times ſtood ſtately ſeat<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>No memory ſhould of their ſtate remaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But He that ſwaies eternally this ball,</l>
                  <l>By iuſtice fixt his euerlaſting throne,</l>
                  <l n="8">8 To diſtribute the lawes by righting all,</l>
                  <l>And ruling men that each may haue his owne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 When force doth ſit to hatch high-ſwelling pride,</l>
                  <l>Thy gate of Grace ſtands open for the poore,</l>
                  <l>Thy caſtle of ſafe refuge thou ſet'ſt wide,</l>
                  <l>That all diſtreſt may enter at the doore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 And therefore well may they in Thee alone,</l>
                  <l>Who know thy wide-ſpread Name, their truſt repoſe,</l>
                  <l>When all the world hath by experience knowne,</l>
                  <l>Thou leau'ſt not thine to'h mercy of their foes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 Then ſing due praiſe vnto the Lord, whoſe hand</l>
                  <l>And watchfull eie keeps his lou'd Sion ſure,</l>
                  <l>Spread wide his wiſe decrees in eu'ry land,</l>
                  <l>Them let no bounds leſſe than the world immure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 For guiltleſſe bloud he takes a ſtrict account,</l>
                  <l>Reuenging it with plagues, and inward feares,</l>
                  <l>And ſuffers not pride vnreueng'd to mount</l>
                  <l>And preſſe the poor, whoſe cries ſoon pierce his eares.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="13">13 But thou, deare God, look neerer to my cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Whom armed force purſues with deadly ſpight,</l>
                  <l>And take me from the fell and direfull iawes</l>
                  <l>Of Death, whoſe hue is black as pitchy night.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:150662:11"/>
                  <l n="14">14 That all ſo high as Sion lifts her head,</l>
                  <l>And ſets her towers ſo far, ſo wide to view,</l>
                  <l>I man thy name with vowes and praiſes ſpread,</l>
                  <l>And daily thankes for hourely helpe renew.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="15">15 Perfidious wights in waues of ſelfe-bred wrong</l>
                  <l>Toſt, and turmoild, haue worthily been drown'd,</l>
                  <l>And in the nets, which they were knitting long</l>
                  <l>For others laide, themſelues were helpleſſe bound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="16">16 Who but admires Heau'ns-equall ballanc'd right?</l>
                  <l>Who weau'd the web of fraud himſelfe was caught,</l>
                  <l>A thing ſo oft perform'd in all mens ſight</l>
                  <l>Should be enrould and kept in inward thought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="17">17 But ſo it is. Time not fore-ſeene arreſts</l>
                  <l>The god-leſſe men, who haue not Heau'n in mind,</l>
                  <l>Then ſodaine death wounds their rebellious breaſts,</l>
                  <l>And hides them in his pit where no ſun ſhin'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="18">18 But modeſt minds which breathe but aire diuine,</l>
                  <l>Hopeleſſe of helpe, but what from Heauen deſcends,</l>
                  <l>God in his heart doth them a place aſſigne,</l>
                  <l>Where cauſeleſſe griefe at laſt findes large amends.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="19">19 Vp, vp, Creator of all things, ariſe,</l>
                  <l>And let not man, not many ſpans in length</l>
                  <l>Mount to a monſter of deformed ſize</l>
                  <l>To cruſh the poor, Curb thou mens lawleſſe ſtrength.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="20">20 Thou with the boundleſs weight of endleſs might,</l>
                  <l>Strike horror deep into their fiercer mindes,</l>
                  <l>That man may know his feeble ſtate aright,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe weaker parts no laſting cement bindes.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="ode">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:150662:11"/>
               <head>PSAL. X.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HOw long wilt thou, Conſeruer of mankind,</l>
                  <l>Neglect thy ſeruants in their ſad diſtreſſe?</l>
                  <l n="2">2 How long wilt thou remain in Heauen confin'd,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt Lord-like here lewd men the iuſt oppreſſe?</l>
                  <l>Let ill befall the ill-conceiuing head,</l>
                  <l>And periſh it with all the arts it bred.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Whilſt he with wrongs doth cram his luſtful heart,</l>
                  <l>The proud man boaſts, and inwardly is glad,</l>
                  <l>As he had wonne by right, and vs'd no art,</l>
                  <l>And ſtill ſhould hold the glory that he had.</l>
                  <l n="4">4 Thus his vnbridled arrogance neglects</l>
                  <l>Of right, and wrong the contrary reſpects.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whilſt ſweetly he applauds his in-bred wit,</l>
                  <l>And thinks in Heauen there is no God, nor feares,</l>
                  <l n="5">5 But proudly champing on his pleaſant bit,</l>
                  <l>His happineſſe his haughty hearts vpreares,</l>
                  <l>Nor dreams that thou to iudgment wilt proceede,</l>
                  <l>And vindicate the guilt of his miſ-deed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He ſleights his foes, nor cares for them a ſtraw,</l>
                  <l n="6">6 And reck'ning with himſelfe without his Hoſt,</l>
                  <l>My life, ſaith he, at longeſt length I'le draw,</l>
                  <l>And ſteere my courſe with no rough billowes toſt.</l>
                  <l>No care ſhall come to interrupt my ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Nor fits of paine my pleaſure ſhall abate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 Out of his mouth doe curſed ſlaunders flow,</l>
                  <l>Diſgorging taunts, and crafty wiles withall,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt to good men do griefes and trauailes grow,</l>
                  <l>By his enuenom'd tongue, and bitter gall.</l>
                  <l n="8">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:150662:12"/>8 His ambuſhes to catch the iuſt he laies,</l>
                  <l>And poorer men with ſterner looks affraies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 As a bloud-thirſty Lion in his den</l>
                  <l>Lies couching cloſe, and hides his fearfull head,</l>
                  <l>So lurking he aſſaults the weaker men,</l>
                  <l>His panting heart with fainting fury led,</l>
                  <l>And with his many knotted nets faſt ti'de,</l>
                  <l>He drawes them in as captiues to his pride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 He tames them with his force, won with his wiles,</l>
                  <l>And as in clouds doth he conceale his ſpight;</l>
                  <l>How many troupes of trauailers with guiles</l>
                  <l>Hath he ſurpris'd, and them depriu'd of light?</l>
                  <l>Who paſſing by, when they do think no harm,</l>
                  <l>Are caught vnwares, &amp; cruſh'd with his proud arm.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 He argues thus with reaſons wanting weight,</l>
                  <l>That God his wrongs doth neither ſee, nor know.</l>
                  <l>Doth He, enthrond in clouds of ſupreme height</l>
                  <l>Behold the right, and wrong done here below?</l>
                  <l>Can man conceiue ſo high maieſtick power</l>
                  <l>With ſmiles, or frowns on earth to laugh, or lowre?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 Vp, Lord, and lift thy ſacred hand on high,</l>
                  <l>And with thy powerfull ſword pierce thou his ſide,</l>
                  <l>Nor let thou him in dark obliuion lie</l>
                  <l>Whoſe pious heart doth in thy feare abide.</l>
                  <l>Extend thy grace, and deale thy iuſtice ſo,</l>
                  <l>As meek men may haue bliſſe, and proud men wo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="13">13 Ah ſhall the more then madneſſe of lewd men</l>
                  <l>Contemne thee thus, and ſet thy will at naught,</l>
                  <l>And dare to mutter in their ſecret den</l>
                  <l>That God for humane things doth take no thought?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:150662:12"/>Thus when their mouths are clos'd, and dare not ſpeak,</l>
                  <l>Their hollow hearts are ful of thinks, &amp; leak.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="14">14 Thou ſeeſt without, within, thou vew'ſt all things,</l>
                  <l>And vnder thy ſharp hand ſhall lewd men fall,</l>
                  <l>That by affliction, which true inſight brings,</l>
                  <l>This leſſon they may learne, that ruling all,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſleight'ſt not poor mens griefe, nor toils neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect'ſt,</l>
                  <l>But left to thee the Orphanes thou protect'ſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="15">15 Break thou the force of the vngodly wight,</l>
                  <l>And coole the fury of his graceleſſe mind,</l>
                  <l>Till he, and all the branches of his might,</l>
                  <l>Be broken downe, nor root be left behind,</l>
                  <l>That he, nor they may in the limits ſtand,</l>
                  <l>And compaſſe of the Ocean-bounded land.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="16">16 Thus thou, the Lord of time, till time haue end</l>
                  <l>Shalt rule, and raigne ſole Monarch ouer all,</l>
                  <l>And from the land to which thy bounds extend,</l>
                  <l>Shalt chaſe the Nations that do lewdly fall</l>
                  <l>To impious rites, and ſet thy law aſide,</l>
                  <l>That baniſh'd they may vaniſh with their pride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="17">17 Theſe vowes the men o're-whelm'd with croſſe affaires,</l>
                  <l>Theſe praiers they poure forth with reu'rence due,</l>
                  <l>And ſpurgald with the pricks of deep deſpaires</l>
                  <l>With briniſh teares to thee theſe humbly ſue,</l>
                  <l>(For whom haue they in Heauen &amp; Earth but thee</l>
                  <l>That with a power ſupreme canſt ſet them free?)</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="18">18 To looſe the poore (whom beaſts do pitty more)</l>
                  <l>From the dire bands of mens all-daring might,</l>
                  <l>That man, who doth his arme of fleſh adore,</l>
                  <l>May ſtrike his ſailes, and leaue his fury quite,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:150662:13"/>When he beholds, and conſcious is within</l>
                  <l>Of his fraile ſtate, the web of his foule ſin.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHen I haue hope ſafe harbor to attain,</l>
                  <l>And for my ſtarre on Heauens great Lord relie,</l>
                  <l>Like frighted fowle, which would the couert gaine,</l>
                  <l>You bid mee to the rockes for ſafety flie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 Behold, you ſee, the impious man doth bend</l>
                  <l>His threatning bow, and makes his ſhafts to wound</l>
                  <l>The harmeleſſe ſoule, and cloſely doth attend</l>
                  <l>To murder thoſe whoſe feareleſſe hearts are ſound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 But thou, great King, with thy all-conqu'ring hand</l>
                  <l>The rebells tam'ſt, and doſt diuert their will,</l>
                  <l>Who, mad with rage, vexe thoſe who humbly ſtand</l>
                  <l>At thy deuotion, and deſerue no ill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 God who in Heau'ns eternall temples dwels,</l>
                  <l>And doth in his ſtar-ſpangled throne appeare,</l>
                  <l>With his tranſ-piercing eies, whoſe ſight excells,</l>
                  <l>Viewes all the acts are repreſented here.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 From his all-ſeeing eie nor wrong, nor right</l>
                  <l>Can hidden be, but thoſe who beate their braines</l>
                  <l>To compaſſe miſchiefe, He who rules with might,</l>
                  <l>And right combind, hates all their cunning traines.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 He ſhowreth downe on their deteſted heads</l>
                  <l>His wide ſpread nets, and thundring tempeſts caſts</l>
                  <l>With ſulpher mixt (which the proud'ſt ſcorner dreads)</l>
                  <l>To ſcorch them here, whoſe burning euer laſts.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:150662:13"/>
                  <l n="7">7 But he that foſters right, himſelfe moſt right,</l>
                  <l>With ſacred loue doth vpright men embrace,</l>
                  <l>And ſets before his euerlaſting ſight</l>
                  <l>The rightfull conſcience, where no guile hath place.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HElpe, Sauiour, helpe and be not thou auerſe,</l>
                  <l>Since virgin Faith fall'n now in mens diſgrace,</l>
                  <l n="2">2 Expuls'd is gone, and Truth flees all commerce,</l>
                  <l>And naked ſhuns the Earths diſguiſed race.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now eu'ry man doth entertaine his friend</l>
                  <l>With words, the ſcum, and fume of idle brains,</l>
                  <l>And cloakes the wrongs which falſer hearts entend,</l>
                  <l>With lies which ſmooth diſſimulation fains.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Deceitfull mouthes whence ſugred poiſon flowes,</l>
                  <l>Let God confound, and plucke out root, and all,</l>
                  <l>The tongue that doth the hearts baſe births diſcloſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſpeakes great things although it ſelfe be ſmall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 And periſh they with braſen browes, who ſay,</l>
                  <l>What ſhould we feare, come let vs ſweare, and lye,</l>
                  <l>That periury, by cuſtome bearing ſway,</l>
                  <l>Our tongues may venture on all villany.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No Lord, I think, hath any thing to ſhew</l>
                  <l>My free borne tongue in vaſſalage to hold,</l>
                  <l>Nor lock my lips, nor bar my language ſo,</l>
                  <l>As not to range at pleaſure vncontrold.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 But God that heares the plaints of poor diſtreſs'd,</l>
                  <l>And burthen-bearing ſoules that ſigh for griefe,</l>
                  <l>Ariſe will I, ſaith He, and them oppreſs'd.</l>
                  <l>Securely place in harbour of reliefe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:150662:14"/>
                  <l n="6">6 This ſaith the Lord, and what from him proceeds</l>
                  <l>His faith is fixt like gold, which ſeuen-times tri'de</l>
                  <l>By purging fire, no more refining needs,</l>
                  <l>When ſmoke, and aſhes do the droſſe diuide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 Then mindfull of thy promiſe, Lord, reſtraine</l>
                  <l>The cure-leſſe poiſon of a curſed tongue,</l>
                  <l>And thou, the worlds beſt Sentinell, containe</l>
                  <l>The viperous race that we may not be ſtongue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 For lewd men now giue law, and meaſure right</l>
                  <l>By their owne foot, and dominering will,</l>
                  <l>And gouern'd by their diſproportion'd might</l>
                  <l>The beſt men feare the doomes of men moſt ill.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HOw long wilt thou, who guid'ſt our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon helm,</l>
                  <l>Neglect my cauſe as one forſaken quite?</l>
                  <l>Wilt thou leaue me whom ſwelling ſurges whelm</l>
                  <l>Wrapt in obliuions euerlaſting might?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How long wilt thou in fierce diſpleaſure hide</l>
                  <l>Thy louely face, and gracefull eye from me?</l>
                  <l>How long ſhall vexing cares which draw aſide</l>
                  <l>My mind from reſt, my ſoules companions be?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 How long ſhall my grieu'd heart with rougher waues</l>
                  <l>In ſeas of deep afflictions thus be toſt?</l>
                  <l>How long ſhall my proud foes, (who are ſins ſlaues)</l>
                  <l>Thus triumph ouer me as all were loſt?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Great Regent of the world behold and ſee,</l>
                  <l>Aſſiſt me, and infuſe thy ſacred light,</l>
                  <l>Leſt Death with his long ſleepe do ceaze on me,</l>
                  <l>And cloſe mine eies, and bid the Sun good night.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150662:14"/>
                  <l n="4">4 Let not my foe brag in his haughty pride,</l>
                  <l>That he hath cruſht me with his brawny armes,</l>
                  <l>And who hate truth, and cannot me abide,</l>
                  <l>Haue they no cauſe to triumph at my harmes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 Thou do'ſt with hope refreſh my drooping heart,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe help extends it ſelfe to all my vaines:</l>
                  <l>When I am ſafe (becauſe thou took'ſt my part)</l>
                  <l>Thy name, great King, I'le ſing with lofty ſtraines.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XIIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>PRoud Pollicy, now making Vice his minion,</l>
                  <l>Inly conceiu'd thus mutters his opinion,</l>
                  <l>And ſaith that feare which keeps the mind in aw,</l>
                  <l>Bred of the froth of melancholy braines</l>
                  <l>Hath made a God, and giuen him the raines</l>
                  <l>Whilſt whirling Chance giues all the world the law.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then did Iniquity that feares no rod</l>
                  <l>Wallow in ſins as if there were no God,</l>
                  <l>And no man had a will to follow right</l>
                  <l n="2">2 But Heauens great Lord caſt down his eie to view</l>
                  <l>Who would, whilſt fooles their vainer cares purſue,</l>
                  <l>Adore his name of maieſty and might.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 There all conſpir'd in miſchiefs of all kinds,</l>
                  <l>Their foule, flagitious, lothſome ſins he finds,</l>
                  <l>Nor was their care in any to do good,</l>
                  <l n="4">4 For how ſhould they do good, or how giue eare</l>
                  <l>To ſound aduice, who ſtill about them beare</l>
                  <l>The plague-ſores of foule ſin, and ſtaines of blood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When as a beaſt his prey, ſo they deuoure</l>
                  <l>My people, if they come within their power,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:150662:15"/>Nor ſerue they God, who ſou'raign rules all things:</l>
                  <l n="5">5 But with chill feare ſhall horror ſtrike their hearts.</l>
                  <l>When the iuſt God takes guiltleſſe iuſt-mens parts,</l>
                  <l>And wounds the impious with ſharp words like ſtings;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 And ſaies, O you made Piety a ieſt,</l>
                  <l>You laugh'd when cares the pious minds oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſcoff'd at their vowes, hopes, and ſilent fears,</l>
                  <l>But God, in whom the poor their truſt repoſe,</l>
                  <l>Their hopes, &amp; vowes which their ſad breſts incloſe,</l>
                  <l>Vnto their wiſhed ends he fairly ſtears.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 O then that God to his would ſuccour ſend,</l>
                  <l>Which longing they from Sion hill attend,</l>
                  <l>For when he breaks their bonds, and them acquits,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Abra'ms</hi> race, ſhall with a cheerfull breſt</l>
                  <l>Ioy, and enioy their long deſired reſt,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Is'acs</hi> race ſhall triumph as befits.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XV.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHo ſacred Sions temple by thy will,</l>
                  <l>Heau'ns ſupreme Lord, inhabit ſhall with Thee?</l>
                  <l>And whom wilt thou place on thy holy hill,</l>
                  <l>To liue in ſweet repoſe from dangers free?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 He that delights to haue an honeſt heart,</l>
                  <l>And ſtiffe in what he vndertakes does right,</l>
                  <l>Nor faire in ſhew, with counterfeiting art</l>
                  <l>Hath taught his tongue how to conceale his ſpight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Nor with his lips doth deadly draughts contriue,</l>
                  <l>Nor miſchiefe to his neighbour doth deuiſe,</l>
                  <l>Nor doth his friend, who ſeems endear'd depriue</l>
                  <l>Of his good name with his opprobrious lies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:150662:15"/>
                  <l n="4">4 Who caſts no eye of fauour on the proud,</l>
                  <l>But takes into the cloſſet of his heart</l>
                  <l>The Heauen-grac'd man. Who minding what he vow'd,</l>
                  <l>Not for a world will from his word depart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 Who lends not mony, nor takes biting vſe</l>
                  <l>To make the poore a prey caught in his nets,</l>
                  <l>Who for reward will offer no abuſe</l>
                  <l>To harmleſſe men. Who thus his compaſſe ſets</l>
                  <l>To leade his life, thus makes his laſt account,</l>
                  <l>Shall euer reſt within the holy Mount.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XVI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Thou Creator of all things below,</l>
                  <l>And mens ſafe harbour in their dire diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſeruant ſaue, who doth no Sauiour know,</l>
                  <l>But thee alone when inſtant perills preſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 Thy ſeruant I, do thee my Lord auow,</l>
                  <l>And tell abroad what a great Lord thou art,</l>
                  <l>But whom all bleſſe, and to whom all things bow,</l>
                  <l>What good to thee can all I do impart?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 I therefore there my vtmoſt powers appli'd<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>To tend the people with a zealous care,</l>
                  <l>The people which of all the world beſide</l>
                  <l>Thou took'ſt to thee for thy peculiar ſhare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 But they rebell'd vnmindfull of thy grace,</l>
                  <l>And to themſelues apart new gods did faine,</l>
                  <l>Which they ador'd, and proſtrate on their face</l>
                  <l>Idol'd the dreames of their owne idle braine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:150662:16"/>
                  <l>Their altars ſtain'd with bloud will I not tuch,</l>
                  <l>Nor in their feaſts doth my ſoule take delight,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall their names (profanely vs'd too much,)</l>
                  <l>Be witneſſe of my words, or faith I plight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 But Gods right hand of laſting loue ſhall ſhield</l>
                  <l>The people which his grace to me aſſign'd,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch reward me ſhall his bounty yeeld</l>
                  <l>As for my paines euen Hope diſpair'd to find.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 How beautious are the bounds which I poſſeſſe</l>
                  <l>In what a field doth Heauen my lot diſpoſe?</l>
                  <l>Seated where pleaſure doth her ſelf addreſſe,</l>
                  <l>And feeds my mind with flowers ſweet-ſmiling ſhowes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 To God eternall be all endleſſe praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe counſell doth direct me in the light,</l>
                  <l>And brings into my ſoule by priuy waies</l>
                  <l>His Heauen-ſpir'd motions in the darkeſt night.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 What ſo my heart doth think, or hand doth act</l>
                  <l>I ſee the Lord aſſiſting ſtill at hand,</l>
                  <l>Guarded before, on either ſide, and backt</l>
                  <l>By him, and him alone, I ſteaddy ſtand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 My trembling heart ſo quauers in my breſt</l>
                  <l>The noates of ioy, as that my tongue delights</l>
                  <l>To ſing thy praiſe, and ſo before ſuppreſt</l>
                  <l>A lightſome hope my lumpiſh lims excites.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 For neither wilt thou leaue my ſoule to bide</l>
                  <l>In helliſh vaults, where neuer comes thy light,</l>
                  <l>Nor let it like a carcaſſe putrifi'de</l>
                  <l>Reſolu'd to aſhes be conſumed quite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:150662:16"/>
                  <l n="11">11 Thou to the way of life vnlock'ſt the gate,</l>
                  <l>And from thy face high tides of ioy do ſpring,</l>
                  <l>From thy right hand where bounty keeps her ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Thy bleſſings flow which all delights do bring.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XVII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHo rul'ſt the world, and all things do'ſt direct,</l>
                  <l>Heare righteous Lord what righteouſly I craue,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſtop thine eares, nor do my plaints reiect</l>
                  <l>Which come not from ſuch lips as Liers haue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 Poore I diſtreſt vnto thy throne do flie,</l>
                  <l>Take thou my cauſe in hand, on thee I call,</l>
                  <l>Proſtrate before thy face, with gracefull eie</l>
                  <l>See iuſt men here vniuſtly dealt withall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Thou often view'ſt through clouds of ſilent night</l>
                  <l>With curious ſearch the ſecrets of my mind,</l>
                  <l>And how my heart put in a feariſh fright,</l>
                  <l>And ſhaking fit no reſt at all could find.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As fire doth gold, ſo thou my heart do'ſt trie</l>
                  <l>With croſſe euents, nor didſt thou find the ſame</l>
                  <l>Conſcious of fraud, or lawleſſe villany</l>
                  <l>To wrong euen ſuch as branded were with ſhame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 My mouth, and mind agreed, my ſoule, and ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>My heart vpheld by thy decrees diuine</l>
                  <l>Abhors foule ſin, that giues ſo foule offence,</l>
                  <l>And flies from pride, which doth with wrong combine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 Thus guide my ſteps led by thy lawes aduice</l>
                  <l>Leſt that my foot ſlip in a doubtfull way,</l>
                  <l>Or in ſuch paths as ſeeme all pau'd with ice</l>
                  <l>My footing ſlide, where it can find no ſtay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:150662:17"/>
                  <l n="6">6 I call to thee, and fly vnto thy grace</l>
                  <l>Which I haue often tri'de in dire diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Attentiue lend thine eare in my ſad caſe,</l>
                  <l>When I by praier my plaints to thee addreſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 With grace, good Lord, ſupport, and bear vp thoſe</l>
                  <l>Whoſe hope and helpe on thee alone doth ſtand,</l>
                  <l>And curbe the lofty ſpirits of my foes,</l>
                  <l>And iuſtly mou'd vſe thy reuengefull hand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 But guard me like the apple of thine eye</l>
                  <l>More deare, and tender than all parts beſide,</l>
                  <l>And thou that do'ſt foreſee all dangers nye,</l>
                  <l>Vnder thy wings me from proud fury hide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 The troope of impious men ſtand ready preſt</l>
                  <l>At all aſſaies to take away my breath,</l>
                  <l n="10">10 And me with force beleguer, and infeſt</l>
                  <l>With ſwelling words, and dart their threats of death.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 They make their barres, and turn-pikes in the way,</l>
                  <l>And view the places that may moſt offend,</l>
                  <l>Which they deſigne to make my life their pray,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeming not to minde it, worke mine end,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 Like as a lion hunting beaſts, or men,</l>
                  <l>Runs furious on, or like vnto his ſire,</l>
                  <l>The wean'd whelp lurks, and glowting in the den</l>
                  <l>Long looks with blood to cool his raging fire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="13">13 Vp, Father, vp, their lewd attempts preuent,</l>
                  <l>And whilſt the Tyrant trampled lies on ground,</l>
                  <l>Free thou me from thy ſword (to mercy bent)</l>
                  <l>Wherewith he now enrag'd doth ſtrike, and wound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:150662:17"/>
                  <l n="14">14 Nor let the pride of great men ctam'd with gold</l>
                  <l>With might oppreſſe me, whoſe delightfull care</l>
                  <l>Is but to wallow (as themſelues are mold)</l>
                  <l>In earthly pleaſures, ſo bewitcht they are.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou pour'ſt on them thy bleſſings from thy ſtore</l>
                  <l>Digg'd from the bowells of the earth below,</l>
                  <l>And pamp'reſt them with corne, and, which is more,</l>
                  <l>Thou glad'ſt their hearts their off-ſpring proſpers ſo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="15">15 Then ſhall the candor of my life make way,</l>
                  <l>That I loos'd from the bodies gyue, and free</l>
                  <l>Shall ſee thy face, and that bright ſhining day</l>
                  <l>Shall make me bleſt, all-bleſt in high'ſt degree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="16">16 Thoſe beames of light, which brings all ſound de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light,</l>
                  <l>Heap'd with all ioies, ſhall repreſent thy cleare,</l>
                  <l>And ſacred Maieſty vnto my ſight,</l>
                  <l>When as no cloud ſhall in my mind appeare.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XVIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>All-foſtring Sire, I'le thee adore,</l>
                  <l>And will thee loue with all my heart,</l>
                  <l n="2">2 Who ſhap'dſt the world a lump before,</l>
                  <l>My ſtrength, my might, my tower thou art,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Help, hope, and ioy to me diſtreſt,</l>
                  <l>My ſhield, my ſword, my ſteaddy ſtay,</l>
                  <l>An anchor fixt whereon I reſt,</l>
                  <l>And when ſtormes come my calmeſt bay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 For when my tongue I do vntye,</l>
                  <l>Which crauing peace thy praiſes ſings,</l>
                  <l>All hoſtile armes are then laid by,</l>
                  <l>And Peace brings ſafety on her wings.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:150662:18"/>
                  <l n="4">4 Now Death enuolu'd me in his net,</l>
                  <l>With Hell-black ſtreames encompaſt round,</l>
                  <l n="5">5 Infernall ſnares my feet beſet,</l>
                  <l>And drawn was I with fetters bound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 Here taken, and entangled ſo,</l>
                  <l>Groueling on ground to God I ſu'd,</l>
                  <l>Aloft to Heau'n my cries did goe</l>
                  <l>When doubtfull chance my fears renew'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Seated on his flame-circled throne</l>
                  <l>He heard my praiers, when as my cry</l>
                  <l>Did pierce the skies, and to my moane</l>
                  <l>He bent his eare, and laid it nigh.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 The Earth affrighted at his ſight</l>
                  <l>Shook then, and hills their cloſures brake,</l>
                  <l>And all their ioints diſſolued quite</l>
                  <l>In their low vaults a bellowing make.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 A ſmoaking heate, like breath neer ſpent,</l>
                  <l>Fum'd from his noſtrils flames that turn'd</l>
                  <l>As doth a whirpoole from him went,</l>
                  <l>And what they toucht ſcapt not vnburn'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 Heau'n at his beck bow'd humbly low,</l>
                  <l>To ſet his Lord on th' earthes round ball,</l>
                  <l>And foggy clouds that ſullen ſhow</l>
                  <l>Vnder his feet do proſtrate fall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 He in his chariot mounted hie,</l>
                  <l>In flames an Angell holds the raine,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe wings of winde do ſwifter fly</l>
                  <l>Than oares can cut the liquid maine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:150662:18"/>
                  <l n="11">11 Inuolud in miſts of ſable hue,</l>
                  <l>He hides from Earth his brighter face,</l>
                  <l>In hollow clouds that ſtormes renue,</l>
                  <l>The pitchy waues obſcure his grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 Fire-flinging darts from his ſharp eies</l>
                  <l>Cleere lowring clouds with cheering beames,</l>
                  <l>A ratling ſhowre of haile-ſtones flies,</l>
                  <l>And flitting flames caſt winding ſtreames.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="13">13 But when his voice ſad ſilence brake</l>
                  <l>His thunder roares, and rends the skie,</l>
                  <l>The Earth with ſtormy haile did make</l>
                  <l>An hideous noiſe: Out lightnings flie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="14">14 His firy ſhafts flew far, and wide</l>
                  <l n="15">15 In th' aires vaſt vaults, lights took no reſt:</l>
                  <l>He ſtrikes, and th' Earths wide chaps diuide,</l>
                  <l>And ſhew the ſprings hid in her breſt,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And opens all the fountaine-heads,</l>
                  <l>Trembling for feare ſhe ſhowes how low</l>
                  <l>The ſtrength of her foundation ſpreads,</l>
                  <l>And brings the darkeſt deepe to ſhow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So thundring flies his roaring ſound,</l>
                  <l>So heauy falls his frightfull ire;</l>
                  <l n="16">16 His hand that doth with grace abound</l>
                  <l>He ſtretcht from Heau'n at my deſire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And took me vp when almoſt drown'd,</l>
                  <l>Swift waues had ouer-whelmed me,</l>
                  <l n="17">17 And from my foes, for force renown'd,</l>
                  <l>With greater force He ſet me free,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:150662:19"/>
                  <l n="18">18 And with their power He mock'd their ſpight,</l>
                  <l>When in their harmefull madding mood</l>
                  <l>They ſought by craft, as dark as night,</l>
                  <l>To ruine me who ſtaggring ſtood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="19">19 He gaue me aide, enlarg'd my way</l>
                  <l>When ſtraights before did me encloſe,</l>
                  <l>And when Death had me at a bay</l>
                  <l>He ſau'd his friend whom He had choſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="20">20 My heart, and hand from falſhood free</l>
                  <l>His eies did pierce, and found them ſo,</l>
                  <l>And rais'd me high from low degree</l>
                  <l>That Honour might true vertue ſhow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="21">21 For vice nor errour prone to ill</l>
                  <l>Did make my ſteps to goe aſtray,</l>
                  <l n="22">22 His Law that doth preſcribe his will</l>
                  <l>Was in my ſight ſtill night, and day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whoſe preſence kept my ſoule in awe</l>
                  <l>Thundring her precepts in my heart;</l>
                  <l n="23">23 In truth that hath nor crack, nor flaw,</l>
                  <l>I took delight, ſhe took my part</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As witneſſe, when that inly free</l>
                  <l>From fraud, and guile I ſhunn'd the arts,</l>
                  <l>The curſed arts that ſinke-hoals be</l>
                  <l>Whence flowes foule ſin that ſoiles all parts.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="24">24 His bleſſings therefore did He giue,</l>
                  <l>His bounties ſhew'd how He regards</l>
                  <l>The guiltleſſe life which I did liue,</l>
                  <l>And which th' all-ſeeing Iudge rewards.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:150662:19"/>
                  <l n="25">25 As Men, and as their manners be,</l>
                  <l>So do they find thee harſh, or kind,</l>
                  <l>Nor harme to h'harmleſſe comes from Thee,</l>
                  <l>Whom ſtill a friend, thy friends ſhall find:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="26">26 To good men good, but who would gaine</l>
                  <l>Ought at thy hand by ſleight of wit,</l>
                  <l>Thy wider reach proues his but vaine,</l>
                  <l>And him not wiſe that truſts to it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="27">27 In hard diſtreſſe thou keep'ſt the rent,</l>
                  <l>And worne eſtate of thine growne low,</l>
                  <l>And mak ſt to fall the lofty bent</l>
                  <l>Of the proud eie of my fell foe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="28">28 And taken from the throng of thoſe</l>
                  <l>That baſer be, Thou do'ſt me place</l>
                  <l>Aboue the reſt in ſolemne ſhowes,</l>
                  <l>And clear'ſt my night with thy bright face:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="29">29 And vnder thy command the troops</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> break, and paſſe their glittring armes,</l>
                  <l>The towring'ſt mount to me it ſtoopes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſcale their walls, and ſcape their harmes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="30">30 As true as God is only good,</l>
                  <l>He ſhowes to life the ſhorteſt way,</l>
                  <l>And cleereſt from expence of blood</l>
                  <l>To thoſe that with his colours ſtay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From his eternall mouth what flowes</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> far more pure than refin'd gold,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd with his ſhield He guards all thoſe</l>
                  <l>Whoſe hearts in him confirm'd are bold.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:150662:20"/>
                  <l>He bids them not to be diſmai'd</l>
                  <l>When things ſucceed not to their minds,</l>
                  <l>Since nought on Earth can make affrai'd</l>
                  <l>That heart in Heauen that refuge finds.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="31">31 Say you who painted ſtocks adore</l>
                  <l>The mock-minds of the vulgar rout,</l>
                  <l>Who ſtones and iu'ry do implore</l>
                  <l>In ſundry ſhapes with art cut out.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What other God doth rule the raines?</l>
                  <l>Who elſe doth guide the Earths round ball,</l>
                  <l>And ſits in Heau'n that all containes?</l>
                  <l>Whoſe hand but his rules all in all?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="32">32 This God giues ſtrength to all my parts,</l>
                  <l>And liuely force, and ſhewes to me</l>
                  <l n="33">33 The ſpotleſſe way. By Him with Harts</l>
                  <l>In ſwiftneſſe I contend, and He</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Conuai'd me far from dangers neare,</l>
                  <l>And plac'd me high on ſafties hill,</l>
                  <l n="34">34 And taught my hand deuoid of feare</l>
                  <l>To manage armes with vſefull skill:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And beſides that, He made me bend</l>
                  <l>A maſſie bow made all of braſſe,</l>
                  <l>And it to peeces break, and rend;</l>
                  <l>So ſtrong was I, ſo weake it was.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="35">35 He guardes me round on eu'ry ſide</l>
                  <l>With the defence of his ſafe ſhield,</l>
                  <l>His grace makes his right-hand my guide</l>
                  <l>Trebling my ſtrength when I would yeeld.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:150662:20"/>
                  <l n="36">36 He opens me a wide retreit,</l>
                  <l>In paſſages where men do lay</l>
                  <l>Cloſe ambuſhes, traps of deceit:</l>
                  <l>Nor lets my feet wilde wandring ſtay,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Or take offence in vnknowne waies</l>
                  <l n="37">37 And I by thine auſpicious hand</l>
                  <l>Purſue my foes, breake their arraies,</l>
                  <l>And take them when as they disband.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor do I back returne before</l>
                  <l>Their daring minds are brought ſo low,</l>
                  <l>As, though at firſt they threatned ſore,</l>
                  <l>Their courage cool'd it was not ſo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="38">38 And at my feet down let them fall</l>
                  <l>That they may neuer riſe againe,</l>
                  <l>Nor with their armes, or engines all</l>
                  <l>Repaire the loſſe that they ſuſtaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="39">39 Thou through my members mak'ſt to flow</l>
                  <l>A liuely vigour, and haſt ſteel'd</l>
                  <l>My nerues with ſtrength, and do'ſt me ſhow</l>
                  <l>The art to march in Mars his field.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And me who dares come to defie</l>
                  <l n="40">40 Thou lai'ſt him groueling on the ground,</l>
                  <l>And mak'ſt my foes for feare to flye,</l>
                  <l>And none to heare their yelling ſound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="41">41 And ſo, of Thee if they craue aide,</l>
                  <l>Thou turn'ſt thine eare from their requeſt,</l>
                  <l n="42">42 And as the Noth-winde hardly laide</l>
                  <l>Driues to, and fro, and giues no reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:150662:21"/>
                  <l>Vnto a cloud of duſt, ſo I</l>
                  <l>My foes diſrankt force to retire,</l>
                  <l>And trample on them as they lie,</l>
                  <l>As in foule waies men ſtampe the mire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="43">43 Me from the vulgar rout thou tak'ſt</l>
                  <l>Free from their baſe and ſurly aw,</l>
                  <l>And as for my proud foes thou mak'ſt</l>
                  <l>Me put a ſnaffle in their iaw.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To creep and crouch, my grace to ſeek</l>
                  <l n="44">44 Thou mak'ſt the Nations come from far,</l>
                  <l>Fame ſtrikes a paleneſſe in the cheek,</l>
                  <l>And daunted at my name they ar.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="45">45 With words compos'd to gaine them grace</l>
                  <l>Their oylye tongues do ſmoothly flow,</l>
                  <l>Nor thinke themſelues ſafe in a place</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſtrength is ſuch as feares no foe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="46">46 Be to the Lord, rule, honour, praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Who ſhields me circled with his might,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe hand of help to health doth raiſe</l>
                  <l>My weakned lims from Deaths neere ſpight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="47">47 Who with reuenging armes in hand</l>
                  <l>Makes me confound what's lewd, and ill,</l>
                  <l>And makes that (whilſt none dare withſtand)</l>
                  <l>The people yeeld all to my will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And on his word He bid me caſt</l>
                  <l>All feare aſide of bluſtring warre,</l>
                  <l>And when the bounds of awe be paſt,</l>
                  <l>And rage doth raiſe a ciuill iarre,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:150662:21"/>
                  <l n="48">48 He guardes me from the rebell rout:</l>
                  <l>As in a morter pounded ſmall</l>
                  <l>He beats the plots they fetch about,</l>
                  <l>The filthy froth of their foule gall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="46">46 Then to the neighb'ring cities I</l>
                  <l>Will wide thy noble acts extend,</l>
                  <l>And, ſacred Sire, thy praiſe ſhall flye</l>
                  <l>Sung by my Muſe to the worlds end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="50">50 Who bidd'ſt the King reſt ſafe, and ſound,</l>
                  <l>Nor be diſmaid with croſſe ſucceſſe,</l>
                  <l>And mak'ſt him with worlds wealth abound,</l>
                  <l>And with much kindneſſe do'ſt profeſſe,</l>
                  <l>That him, and his till time haue end,</l>
                  <l>Cloſs'd in thin armes thou wilt defend.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XIX.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YOu ſenſleſſe race, ſelfe-ſeeming wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Though impious errour darke your ſights,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſee with eye, and mind the skies</l>
                  <l>Beſpangled with a world of lights.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hence learne his art whoſe hand adornes,</l>
                  <l>And in a vault of fiery flames</l>
                  <l>His temples plac'd, whoſe bending hornes</l>
                  <l>Compaſſe the ſeas, and lands wide frames.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 Where enter change of night, and day</l>
                  <l>By conſtant courſe doth teach below,</l>
                  <l>That mortall things which ſoone decay,</l>
                  <l>Not here by chance, but counſell goe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:150662:22"/>
                  <l>Where eu'ry part plac'd in due frame</l>
                  <l>Sounds Gods all guarding powerfull hand,</l>
                  <l n="3">3 And whiſper not, but cry the ſame</l>
                  <l>That all that heares may vnderſtand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 For in the worlds remoteſt parts</l>
                  <l>No ſauage Nation dwells ſo far,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe eies ſee not, and makes their hearts</l>
                  <l>Confeſſe the Heau'ns right guided ar.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who when at night no clouds be neare</l>
                  <l>Doth not bright-ſhining ſtars admire?</l>
                  <l n="5">5 Or when he ſees the Sun appeare</l>
                  <l>Mounting his chariot red as fire?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When rowſed from his Eaſterne bed</l>
                  <l>His orient looks ſhow bride-groome like,</l>
                  <l>Glittring in gold, and on his head</l>
                  <l>A crowne whoſe ſparkes amazement ſtrike.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Or when he gallops in his race,</l>
                  <l>And cuts the time in equall ſhares,</l>
                  <l>In lims, and ſtrength, and fiercer pace</l>
                  <l>Moſt Giant-like He furious fares.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 Who from the Eaſt to'h Weſtern gole</l>
                  <l>Doth paſſing by the oblique ſignes,</l>
                  <l>With heate giue all a quickning ſoule,</l>
                  <l>And keepes in ſtate that none declines.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 But the due courſe, and comely grace</l>
                  <l>Of other things draw not our ſight,</l>
                  <l>As doth his law, where it takes place,</l>
                  <l>Guide by cloſe raines mens mindes aright.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:150662:22"/>
                  <l>Whoſe promiſes, which conſtant ſtand,</l>
                  <l>By light of truth confirme the mind,</l>
                  <l n="8">8 And by whoſe ſweet ſin-wounding hand,</l>
                  <l>More gaine than paine, or loſſe we find.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And of his lawes the ſacred lights</l>
                  <l>Vnuaile the minds, and bodies eies,</l>
                  <l n="9">9 And faith profeſt with holy rites,</l>
                  <l>Drawes awefull feare that neuer dies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 And right, and conſcious truth in braſſe</l>
                  <l>Do keep thy ſtatutes all enrol'd,</l>
                  <l>Which hony do in ſweetneſſe paſſe,</l>
                  <l>And better are, than gems, or gold.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 Engrauen in his inmoſt parts</l>
                  <l>Thy ſeruant keepes them night and day,</l>
                  <l>And knowes that they, whoſe faithfull hearts</l>
                  <l>Preſerue them, ſhall haue full, full-pay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 His wandring waies who calls to mind?</l>
                  <l>What force of wit can finde them out?</l>
                  <l>Then purge the ſoiles which ſin by kind</l>
                  <l>A winding Serpent, ſhedds about.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="13">13 Let not the force of ſurly pride</l>
                  <l>Hold now the raines, and rule my heart:</l>
                  <l>So ſhalt thou ſoone looſe me faſt ti'd,</l>
                  <l>With worſt of ills bound eu'ry part.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="14">14 The words which from my tongue do flow,</l>
                  <l>What inlye doth my mind record</l>
                  <l>Benignely heare, O Thee I know</l>
                  <l>My ſtrength, my Sauiour, God, and Lord.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="ode">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:150662:23"/>
               <head>PSAL. XX.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THough that the mad, and bloudy ſauage rout</l>
                  <l>With ſword, and flame rage ſpoiling far, and wide,</l>
                  <l>Yeeld not, but goe more daring on, and ſtout,</l>
                  <l>He'l heare thy praiers, who the round globe doth guide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And as He good, and milde heard in diſtreſſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iacob</hi> when He with hands to Heau'n cri'de lowd,</l>
                  <l n="2">2 So will he thee, and his wide power expreſſe,</l>
                  <l>And free thee from thy foes though ne're ſo proud.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With ſecret force He will giue thee full ſtrength</l>
                  <l>From out the ſacred temple where he dwels,</l>
                  <l>Thy drooping heart He will confirme at length</l>
                  <l>From Sion hill where his high power excells.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 He thy deſires will bleſſe, and keep in mind</l>
                  <l>The free oblations of thy purer hand,</l>
                  <l>Thy offrings ſhall with him faire paſſage find,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall thy ſlaughtred beaſts a minute ſtand,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Before the greedy flames on them haue fed,</l>
                  <l>And rais'd their bloudy colours in the skies.</l>
                  <l n="4">4 He'l crowne thy hopes, and all ſhall ſoone be ſped,</l>
                  <l>As thou thy ſelfe could'ſt wiſh, or beſt deuiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 The Lord to vs return'd will we applaud,</l>
                  <l>And ſerue our owne God with his own due rites,</l>
                  <l>Each place ſhall thanks, and to Gods name giue laud,</l>
                  <l>Aſſign'd for ſacred vſe, gaine, or delights.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What ſo with hallow'd lips we humbly craue,</l>
                  <l>He of his grace will giue his free conſent,</l>
                  <l>All ſhall a good, and happy iſſue haue,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall iuſt praiers fall ſhort of their intent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:150662:23"/>
                  <l n="6">6 I know, nor doth my Calender deceiue,</l>
                  <l>The Lord his King in ſafety backe will guide,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall his hand, his pow'rfull hand, thee leaue,</l>
                  <l>When He Heauens ſacred temple opens wide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 Let Syria brag, and troop her Chariot bands</l>
                  <l>Arm'd with ſharp ſiths vpon the axeltree,</l>
                  <l>And on her courſer which on no ground ſtands,</l>
                  <l>Stamps, and cornets, let Perſias boldneſſe be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Truſt He in wheels, He in his hoofes, but we</l>
                  <l>Will call on God, who ſhoots his flames, and thunder,</l>
                  <l n="8">8 Nor horſe, nor chariot ſhall their ſafeguard be,</l>
                  <l>But Vulturs clawes ſhall rend their lims aſunder.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy grace ſhall raiſe vs when we lie full low,</l>
                  <l>And ſet vs on our feet againe vpright:</l>
                  <l n="9">9 Help, Sou'raigne, help, for if Thou fauour ſhow,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſeek we aide, nor feare we any ſpight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He will reſpect, and at all times of need,</l>
                  <l>(A King moſt gracious to his ſubiects deare)</l>
                  <l>He to their humble ſuites will giue good heed,</l>
                  <l>And ſoone his grant ſhall make his grace appeare.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:150662:24"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:150662:24"/>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="ode">
               <pb facs="tcp:150662:25"/>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:150662:25"/>
               <head>PSAL. XXI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOw that the King in triumph rides</l>
                  <l>Free from ſad cares of vexing foes,</l>
                  <l>To thee, Heau'ns King, and none beſides,</l>
                  <l>The honour of the day He owes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou gau'ſt him courage to withſtand</l>
                  <l>The toiles, and hazards of the field,</l>
                  <l>And brought'ſt him back led by thy hand,</l>
                  <l>Whom in his flight thy Grace did ſhield.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 Nor thou deni'dſt what humbly He</l>
                  <l>Implor'd, nor didſt his plaints reiect,</l>
                  <l>Nor what in heart he wiſh'd ſhould be,</l>
                  <l>Return'd in vaine by thy neglect.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 More then he wiſh'd for, and before,</l>
                  <l>Thou powr'dſt on him all bleſſings downe,</l>
                  <l>And on his head, to grace him more,</l>
                  <l>Neuer wore King a richer crowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 He ask'd thee life, and thou didſt giue</l>
                  <l>For death a life that neuer dies;</l>
                  <l n="5">5 In high renowne thou mak'ſt him liue,</l>
                  <l>And ſhine to dazle Enuies eies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 Him did thy Grace a patterne make</l>
                  <l>Of happineſſe to th'after-breed,</l>
                  <l>That mothers thence might meaſure take,</l>
                  <l>When as they bleſſe their hopefull ſeed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 Thou art the Anchor of his truſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſafeſt hauen in rougheſt ſeas,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:150662:26"/>Fixt on thy helpe he feares no guſt,</l>
                  <l>And free from harmes he liues at eaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 Thou wilt his foes both apprehend,</l>
                  <l>And as a Iudge inflict their paines.</l>
                  <l n="9">9 As flames pent cloſe do more extend,</l>
                  <l>When burſting forth they get the raines,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And burne the aged armes of trees;</l>
                  <l>So ſhall the blaſts of thy iuſt ire</l>
                  <l>Conſume thy foes, who thy decrees</l>
                  <l>Contemne, to worke their lewd deſire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 Thou wilt cut downe both root and boughes,</l>
                  <l>The wicked race, and graceleſſe brood,</l>
                  <l n="11">11 Who thee, whilſt they conceiu'd vaine vowes,</l>
                  <l>With bootleſſe force, and fraud withſtood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 Whilſt thou purſu'ſt them in their flight,</l>
                  <l>Their backs the markes of ſhame ſhall beare,</l>
                  <l>And on their face thy darts ſhall light,</l>
                  <l>When from pale death they run for feare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="13">13 O Thou whoſe right-hand holds the reines,</l>
                  <l>And rul'ſt eternall Iudge of all,</l>
                  <l>Vp, let thy foes with pride-fill'd veines</l>
                  <l>Confeſſe thy force, and feele thy gall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then the bleſt troope (worlds Sire) ſhall ſing</l>
                  <l>Of Thee in Hymnes on holidayes,</l>
                  <l>Who milde receiu'ſt the vowes they bring,</l>
                  <l>And lowr'ſt on lewd mens gifts, and layes.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="ode">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:150662:26"/>
               <head>PSAL. XXII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l n="1">1 O God, my God, why leau'ſt Thou me?</l>
                  <l n="2">2 Why leau'ſt Thou me, that thus in vaine</l>
                  <l>My words I ſpend which bootleſſe be?</l>
                  <l>For if the Sunne ſhowes day light plaine,</l>
                  <l>The day ſees how in vaine I cry,</l>
                  <l>And ſo the night, though darke her eye,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet hath ſhe eares to heare me grone,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe with mournfull plaints I fill;</l>
                  <l n="3">3 But Thou art He who dwell'ſt alone</l>
                  <l>In Sion thy deuoted hill.</l>
                  <l n="4">4 Of <hi>Jſ'achs</hi> race thou art the ſong,</l>
                  <l>Our Fathers hope haſt thou beene long.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 Nor who in Thee their truſt did place</l>
                  <l>Went fruſtrate of their hopes from thee,</l>
                  <l>But crauing aide of their ſad caſe,</l>
                  <l>They did profeſſe thou ſett'ſt them free:</l>
                  <l>For they who on thy word relye,</l>
                  <l>The taints, and taunts of foes defie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 But I a wormling am, no man,</l>
                  <l>A ſubiect for the baſeſt tongue,</l>
                  <l>They ſpeake of me the worſt they can,</l>
                  <l>And ſoile my honour with their dongue;</l>
                  <l n="7">7 And in the ſtreet as I paſſe by,</l>
                  <l>But nods, and points naughtelie haue I.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They ſhake their heads, they mumpe, and mow,</l>
                  <l>And with baſe words with points moſt ſharpe,</l>
                  <l>At me their filthy gall they throw,</l>
                  <l n="8">8 Behold, ſay they, (ah thus they carpe)</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:150662:27"/>Gods darling here, who ſafe, and ſure,</l>
                  <l>Thinkes by his helpe to ſtand ſecure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now let him ſaue him if he can,</l>
                  <l>And from neere danger draw him out,</l>
                  <l>Who thinkes himſelfe the onely man,</l>
                  <l>And on his loue doth ſtand ſo ſtout.</l>
                  <l n="9">9 But from the wombe thou took'ſt me, Lord,</l>
                  <l>When firſt thou didd'ſt me light afford.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 On thee in hope I ſtill reli'de,</l>
                  <l>Euen hanging at my mothers breſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeing light, when firſt I cride,</l>
                  <l>My God thou waſt, and ſo doſt reſt;</l>
                  <l n="11">11 Now leaue me not in this my laſt,</l>
                  <l>When danger preſſeth on ſo faſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now is the laſt of all the game,</l>
                  <l>For feare of death friends ſlipp'd aſide:</l>
                  <l n="12">12 Bulls fierce, and fat, (whom none can tame)</l>
                  <l>Did compaſſe me with bellowing pride:</l>
                  <l n="13">13 As Lyons, roaring for their prey,</l>
                  <l>When hope and hunger makes them way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="14">14 In ſtreames of blood my body ſwimmes,</l>
                  <l>Yet bloodleſſe I, and all the bands</l>
                  <l>Of my ioints loos'd, make vſeleſſe limmes,</l>
                  <l>With me like melting waxe it ſtands,</l>
                  <l>As that diſſolues, ſet neere the Sunne,</l>
                  <l>So is my heart with feare vndone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="15">15 My iuiceleſſe members all are dri'd,</l>
                  <l>As potters ſhards burnt in the fire,</l>
                  <l>My tongue to my dry iawes is tyde,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:150662:27"/>And to the graue ſtands no man nier:</l>
                  <l n="16">16 Mad dogs about me barke for ſpite,</l>
                  <l>And with their fangs they pinch, and bite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The worſt of men who 'gainſt me ranke,</l>
                  <l>My hands and feet with piercers bore,</l>
                  <l n="17">17 And through my skinne, growne thinne, and lank,</l>
                  <l>They tell my bones not ſeene before,</l>
                  <l>And though their fury ſpent his ſpite,</l>
                  <l>Yet (their fierce mind fed with delight)</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They make a ſport to glut their eyes,</l>
                  <l n="18">18 And ſee me tortur'd thus: At laſt</l>
                  <l>They ſhar'd my garments as a prize,</l>
                  <l>And on the inmoſt lots they caſt:</l>
                  <l n="19">19 But ſtay the end and me receiue,</l>
                  <l>Nor, Lord, in my laſt languor leaue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou onely art my ſtrength, my might,</l>
                  <l>Then haſt thee, and my life ſuſtaine,</l>
                  <l n="20">20 Support me when all leaue me quite,</l>
                  <l>And my foes bloody ſword reſtraine.</l>
                  <l n="21">21 From foming Dogs their venom'd iawes</l>
                  <l>Saue me, and from the Lyons pawes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="22">22 The hornes of Vnicornes breake thou,</l>
                  <l>So, thy ſuppliant ſau'd from death,</l>
                  <l>To friends, and kinne I will auow</l>
                  <l>That by thy grace I draw my breath.</l>
                  <l>And where thy ſeruants troope, will I</l>
                  <l>Show forth thy Truth, Strength, Maieſty.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="23">23 You that ſerue God with purer minde,</l>
                  <l>Extoll his name with ſober layes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:150662:28"/>And <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſeed, that found him kind,</l>
                  <l>Sing his great power on holy-daies.</l>
                  <l>And you that ſpring from <hi>Iſ'achs</hi> race,</l>
                  <l>To faithfull men confeſſe his grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="24">24 He leaues not him whom men forſake,</l>
                  <l>Nor from the poore turnes He his eye</l>
                  <l>With proud dudaine. When I did make</l>
                  <l>My ſure to him, He paſt not by,</l>
                  <l>But me reſtor'd from fits of paine,</l>
                  <l>Vnto a pleaſing life againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="25">25 Then to the worlds ends yet vnknowne</l>
                  <l>Thy praiſes loud will I reſound,</l>
                  <l>And tell of thee, and thee alone,</l>
                  <l>So far as w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ues the vaſt Earth bound.</l>
                  <l>But pay my vowes will onely where</l>
                  <l>Moſt men adore thy name with feare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="26">26 Where call'd vnto the ſacred feaſt,</l>
                  <l>The ſober troop that knowes no fraud</l>
                  <l>With Nectar fill'd ſhall eu'ry gueſt</l>
                  <l>The Lord of that great feaſt applaud:</l>
                  <l>And with his coſtly cares repleat</l>
                  <l>Acknowledge God who gaue them meat.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And of that God the praiſe ſhall ſing</l>
                  <l>Who enters with Maieſtick grace,</l>
                  <l>And doth a ſparke like vigour bring</l>
                  <l>Into their hearts where it takes place,</l>
                  <l>That feare of death fled far away,</l>
                  <l>There laſting life with ioy ſhould ſtay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="27">27 Then ſhall the Earth, mou'd at the fight</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:150662:28"/>So new, and ſtrange, from pole to pole</l>
                  <l>Be ſubiect to the God of might,</l>
                  <l>And of all kindreds eu'ry ſoule</l>
                  <l>Shall kiſſe his feet, and proſtrate fall,</l>
                  <l>To Him alone the Lord of all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="28">28 To whom of right by fixt decree</l>
                  <l>(Who euerlaſting King is knowne)</l>
                  <l>Belongs this maſſe of Kingdomes three,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe triple Crowne he weares alone,</l>
                  <l>To heauen and hell he giues the law,</l>
                  <l>And all betweene he holds in awe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="29">29 The Greatmen here that rule the reſt,</l>
                  <l>With him as bidden gueſts ſhall ſit,</l>
                  <l>And fill'd with ſweets, fed of the beſt,</l>
                  <l>Shall to his yoke their neckes ſubmit:</l>
                  <l>The which becauſe ſo well they fare,</l>
                  <l>To beare it the more willing are.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The poore who pin'd ſtands neere the graue,</l>
                  <l>Shall bend to him his weakned knee,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe wearied limmes no vigour haue,</l>
                  <l>Nor moiſture left more then hath he</l>
                  <l>Who lying at the point of death,</l>
                  <l>Is yeelding vp his fainting breath.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="30">30 Him ſhall the ofſprings that ſucceed</l>
                  <l>In the long tract of time adore,</l>
                  <l>And tell to all their after-breed,</l>
                  <l>His loue to me ſhew'd long before.</l>
                  <l>This ſeed to him ſhall homage yeeld,</l>
                  <l>And beare his colours in the field.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="ode">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:150662:29"/>
               <head>PSAL. XXIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AT me mad dogs, ah what a coile you keepe?</l>
                  <l>And Enuy why ſett'ſt thou them on to baule?</l>
                  <l>But God keepes me, as Shepheards keepe their ſheepe,</l>
                  <l>Nor do I want, nor can I want at all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 And as a ſheepe I feed, which hath no ſpleene,</l>
                  <l>In paſtures where the ſhort ſweet graſſe doth grow,</l>
                  <l>And where the Spring beflowres his louely greene,</l>
                  <l>My wearied limmes, that ſcarcely ſeru'd to goe,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Refreſh'd againe, I at full eaſe extend.</l>
                  <l n="3">3 The riuer cleare that gliding paſſeth by,</l>
                  <l>Vnto my fainting force doth ſuccours ſend:</l>
                  <l>And in the Sunne when I doe parching lye,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As with a fanne of cooling breath alaies</l>
                  <l>My drooping ſpirits: And when my wandring minde</l>
                  <l>Following the traine of pleaſing Errour, ſtrayes,</l>
                  <l>Tendring his flocke, his way he makes me find.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 And ſhould pale Death, whoſe ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d brings yelling grief</l>
                  <l>Dart at my heart when Hell blacke ſhades affright,</l>
                  <l>I'le folow, Lord, where thou doeſt leade in chiefe,</l>
                  <l>Thy Shepherds ſtaffe will guide me ſafe, and right.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 My table thou doſt with full diſhes ſpre<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d,</l>
                  <l>With ſweeteſt wine my crowned cup o'reflowes,</l>
                  <l>With ſenſe-refreſhing balme thou cheer'ſt my head,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt looking on griefe doth confound my foes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 Me ſhall thy hand of bounty neuer leaue,</l>
                  <l>Nor thy good grace which good men doth attend,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:150662:29"/>And ſo till death doth me of life bereaue,</l>
                  <l>I in thy houſe, my pleaſant daies will ſpend.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XXIV.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Earth is all the Lords, and what beſide</l>
                  <l>It ſparing doth conceale, or bounteous giue,</l>
                  <l>And they are his that in wilde mountaines bide,</l>
                  <l>In fruitfull plaines, and ciuill cities liue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 Vpon the Sea the ſolid Earth he bound,</l>
                  <l>And firmly plac'd it, in ſo weake a ſeat,</l>
                  <l>With ioynts ſo ſtrong, and all the peeces ſound,</l>
                  <l>To bide all brunts, when ſwelling billowes beat.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Thus all belongs vnto the Lord by right,</l>
                  <l>But for himſelfe he hallowed hath a place;</l>
                  <l>And who is he can thither clime? what wight</l>
                  <l>Hath leaue to ſtand within that court of Grace?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 Whoſe heart and hand is cleare, nor idle dreames</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſſe his mind, nor who by ſwearing thriue,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt his falſe oathes ſtript true men of their meanes,</l>
                  <l>Heau'ns Lord to him will Earths beſt bleſſings giue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And by his power ſupreme him will he take,</l>
                  <l>From force, and ſpite, and all they doe, or ſay.</l>
                  <l n="6">6 This, this is Truth, and this alone will make</l>
                  <l>Him ſee Gods face: This leads to heau'n the way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 Vnlock'd, vnbarr'd, you Gates ſtand open wide,</l>
                  <l>Th'eternall Gates, that lead to th'endleſſe throne,</l>
                  <l>Make way, and all that hinders put aſide,</l>
                  <l>Though ſtrong as ſteele, and hard as marble ſtone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:150662:30"/>
                  <l>For that great God, that he may paſſage find,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe glory caſts his ſplendour far and neere.</l>
                  <l n="8">8 For what new gueſt is all this pompe aſſign'd?</l>
                  <l>What King is he whoſe glory ſhines ſo cleare?</l>
                  <l>It is the Lord whoſe glory ſhines ſo far</l>
                  <l>With wealth in peace, with victory in war.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 Vnlock'd, vnbarr'd, you Gates ſtand open wide,</l>
                  <l>Th'eternall gates that lead to th'endleſſe throne,</l>
                  <l>Make way, and all that hinders lay aſide,</l>
                  <l>Though ſtrong as ſteele, or hard as marble ſtone,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For that great God, that he may paſſage finde,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe glory caſts his ſplendour far and neere.</l>
                  <l n="10">10 For what new gueſt is all this pompe aſſign'd?</l>
                  <l>What King is he whoſe glory ſhines ſo cleare?</l>
                  <l>He is the great Commander of the field,</l>
                  <l>To whoſe ſtrong armes all Kings on Earth muſt yeeld.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XXV.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LEt him in armes, another in his traine</l>
                  <l>Of courting followers truſt, and martiall bands,</l>
                  <l>But Thou who mad'ſt what Heau'n and Earth contain,</l>
                  <l>In Thee my hope, in Thee my ſafety ſtands.</l>
                  <l n="2">2 Thou, heauenly Sire, whom I to ſerue haue choſe,</l>
                  <l>Let not my hopes be vaine to pleaſe my foes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Some from ſhames confuſion ſhalt Thou free,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall the bluſhing hue their faces ſtaine,</l>
                  <l>Who fix the ſtaffe of all their truſt in thee:</l>
                  <l>But who loue filth, and filthy will remaine,</l>
                  <l>With ſhame and griefe doe Thou their hopes abate,</l>
                  <l>Who haue no cauſe to vexe me but their hate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:150662:30"/>
                  <l n="4">4 Among ſo many by-paths trod below,</l>
                  <l>Among the brambles, and thicke buſhes here,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſacred way to me thy ſeruant ſhow,</l>
                  <l>And let thy light in darkneſſe now appeare:</l>
                  <l n="5">5 And from the waues of Errour draw me out,</l>
                  <l>Which long, too long, haue compaſt me about.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thence with the light of thy reſplendent beames,</l>
                  <l>Bring me into the way of Truth, and Right,</l>
                  <l>From thy cleare ſpring ſince all my goodneſſe ſtreames,</l>
                  <l>My God, my ſtay, my Sauiour, and delight;</l>
                  <l>Then whilſt alone I doe on Thee depend,</l>
                  <l>Let not my hopes be fruſtrate of their end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6 7">6. 7. Did my lifes rule by crooked vices ſwerue,</l>
                  <l>Or Errour did my ſlipp'ry foot betray,</l>
                  <l>Or did my Youth my vainer pleaſures ſerue,</l>
                  <l>Yet Thou whoſe Grace doth thy fierce rage alay,</l>
                  <l>Pitie my caſe, and what thou maiſt deny</l>
                  <l>To my deſerts, yeeld to thy Clemency.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 Nor Thou the beſt of Good canſt this refuſe,</l>
                  <l>To giue good things to thoſe who ſue to thee,</l>
                  <l>And who deſire the rightfull way to vſe</l>
                  <l>Thou wilt not faile their rule of right to be,</l>
                  <l>For Thou who art Truth, Equity, and Right,</l>
                  <l>Doſt not as men, good will with ill requite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 Thou milde thy ſelfe, Lord, lou'ſt a modeſt mind,</l>
                  <l>And teacheſt it how to diſcerne the iar</l>
                  <l>T'wixt good and ill, (which pride ſeeks not to find)</l>
                  <l>But whilſt there is no concord where they are,</l>
                  <l>Thou by a ſhort and ſafer way the while,</l>
                  <l>Art guide to thoſe who haue no gall, nor guile.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:150662:31"/>
                  <l n="10">10 Sinne thou abhorr'ſt, yet gracious, ſoone forgett'ſt,</l>
                  <l>Thy promiſes thou doſt as franckly pay,</l>
                  <l>And ſparingly thy penalties thou ſett'ſt,</l>
                  <l>And whilſt we not neglect, but firmly ſtay</l>
                  <l>Vpon thy ſacred ſtabliſhments, O Lord,</l>
                  <l>Thy words and works eternally accord.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 That after-ages may record thy grace,</l>
                  <l>That glory thence vnto thy name may ſpring,</l>
                  <l>And ſpread it ſelfe abroad in eu'ry place,</l>
                  <l>Paſſe by our faults, O Father moſt bening,</l>
                  <l>What paſſions, by blind Errour whirl'd about,</l>
                  <l>Haue printed in vs, let thy Grace blot out.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 Thrice happy he who with a guiltleſſe mind</l>
                  <l>Serues thee, O Lord, what courſe ſoe're he takes,</l>
                  <l>He for his compaſſe ſhall thy mercy find,</l>
                  <l>Which in foule ſeas him faireſt paſſage makes,</l>
                  <l>Vntill it bring him to that bleſſed port</l>
                  <l>Where all things well to his beſt wiſhes ſort.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="13">13 Where with a mind without preſumption, bold,</l>
                  <l>He with the beſt of bleſſings ſhall be ſped,</l>
                  <l>Where pillars of faire iſſue ſhall vphold</l>
                  <l>His ancient houſe, and his old ſtock ſhall ſpread,</l>
                  <l>His branches wide, and ſap ſhall ſtill proceed</l>
                  <l>From the freſh root, to bleſſe the after-breed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="14">14 So will the Lord infuſe with ſacred light,</l>
                  <l>His myſteries into the pious mind,</l>
                  <l>And what the godleſſe men contemne, and ſpite,</l>
                  <l>And worldly wits could not by ſearching find,</l>
                  <l>He will reueale the knowledge of his will,</l>
                  <l>The rule of right, and the profoundeſt skill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:150662:31"/>
                  <l n="15">15 Thee therefore, heauens great King, I ſeek, &amp; none</l>
                  <l>But thee alone: Mine eies turne not from thee.</l>
                  <l>Thou wilt my feet (when they are neere vpon</l>
                  <l>The ſnares which my ſlye foes ſhall lay for me)</l>
                  <l>Alone ſo free, and cleare from dangers ſet,</l>
                  <l>As craft ſhall neuer take them in her net.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="16">16 O bleſſed Keeper of the Soules of men,</l>
                  <l>And bodies both, looke with a ſerene eye</l>
                  <l>Vpon me alwaies, but moſt clearly then</l>
                  <l>When all elſe failes whereon I might rely:</l>
                  <l n="17">17 And free my mind from cares which ſore oppreſs,</l>
                  <l>And in their change bring new griefes, but not leſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="18">18 Repell the paines which more and more encreaſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſpare me, Lord, with trauailes ſpent, and worne,</l>
                  <l>Forget my ſinnes, ſo ſhall my pangs ſurceaſe.</l>
                  <l n="19">19 The wicked crue with might not to be borne</l>
                  <l>Purſue my ſoule: O with what ſpite enrag'd,</l>
                  <l>Torment they me, and cannot be aſſwag'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="20">20 Free me from harmes, and, Lord, protect thine own,</l>
                  <l>From ſcorne of thoſe who hate both thee, and thine,</l>
                  <l n="21">21 Since all my wealth depends on thee alone,</l>
                  <l>And I haue nothing that I can call mine</l>
                  <l>To helpe my ſelfe, but onely truſt on Thee,</l>
                  <l>Mine innocence accept, and ſet me free.</l>
                  <l n="22">22 And let the Nation bound vnto thy law,</l>
                  <l>By thy right-hand be clear'd from ſeruile awe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XXVI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVIth open force the Tyrant me purſues,</l>
                  <l>And with cloſe guile at me ſhoots bitter gall,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:150662:32"/>But Thou whoſe eye the hearts darke corners viewes,</l>
                  <l>To thee doe I appeale, great Sire of All.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My mind from fraud is cleare, my hand is cleane,</l>
                  <l>And free from lawleſſe force, or lewd intent,</l>
                  <l>In God I fix my hope, who doth not meane</l>
                  <l>To leaue me ſtill to fortunes furious bent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 Search thou my raines, and inwards of my heart,</l>
                  <l>And the deepe plots lye hidden in my mind,</l>
                  <l>With flames as doe the skilfull artiſts part</l>
                  <l>The droſſe from gold, which they by fire refin'd;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 And thou ſhalt ſee my mind how mindfull ſtill</l>
                  <l>It is of thy munificence, and grace,</l>
                  <l>And how my life directed by thy will,</l>
                  <l>Holds an euen courſe, and keepes a ſober pace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 Hence, hence auant the tongue with falſhood fraught</l>
                  <l>Nor let it think to find a friend of me,</l>
                  <l>And who hath learn'd to paint his inward thought</l>
                  <l>In his flye breſt, far from my houſe be he.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 I hate the counſels of vngracious men,</l>
                  <l>And impious routs then poiſon more deteſt,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe hearts doe leape, as in a triumph, when</l>
                  <l>They doe foule facts, hatch'd in a filthy breſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 But with a mind not conſcious of lewd ſin,</l>
                  <l>And bath'd in pureſt fountaines, I will goe</l>
                  <l>Vnto thy altars, and there leading in</l>
                  <l>The daunce, my ioy will in Oblations ſhow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 My Timbrell, Lute, and voices ſet thereto</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:150662:32"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hall all accord with ioint and ſweet conſent,</l>
                  <l>To tell the youths what wonders thou didd'ſt do,</l>
                  <l>And that in places where they moſt frequent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 The houſe wherein men ſing thy ſacred name,</l>
                  <l>The Temple where thy Godhead men adore,</l>
                  <l>Theſe ſet my mind (long abſent from the ſame,)</l>
                  <l>On fire to ſee thy glorious arke once more.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 Ah let not this prophane vnhallow'd ſoile</l>
                  <l>Among the ſauage beaſts, that thirſt for blood,</l>
                  <l>Couer theſe bones when they ſhall reſt from toile.</l>
                  <l>The men ſo bad, how can the ground be good?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 Their guilefull minds to miſchiefe wholly bent,</l>
                  <l>Hunt after bribes with a deuouring hand,</l>
                  <l n="11">11 But I will ſtill purſue my firſt intent,</l>
                  <l>And in the way of innocence will ſtand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lay thy milde care cloſe to my ſad complaint,</l>
                  <l>And free me from neere dangers that affright,</l>
                  <l n="12">12 That in plaine paths I goe, and doe not faint,</l>
                  <l>But keepe on ſtill, and alwaies follow right,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This is thy gift, this is alone thy grace,</l>
                  <l>And therefore I on high thy name will raiſe,</l>
                  <l>Of thee who art my ſafeties onely baſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the aſſemblies I will ſing thy praiſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XXVII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHen in the dark God guides me w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> his light</l>
                  <l>As with a torch, and he my life protects,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:150662:33"/>What open force, or fury can affright?</l>
                  <l>Or what can feare me, that blind fraud proiects?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 When th'impious rout, in ill that ioine ſo well,</l>
                  <l>Muſtred their troops all againſt me alone,</l>
                  <l>Into the nets themſelues they headlong fell,</l>
                  <l>Where they hop'd I ſhould haue beene ouerthrowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 If Camps entrench'd, if Armies dart their threats,</l>
                  <l>Securely I behold their camps enclos'd,</l>
                  <l>And all their bloody broiles, and warlike feats.</l>
                  <l>I fearleſſe view, with eye, and mind repos'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 One thing I crau'd, and that I euer ſhall,</l>
                  <l>That free from cares which may my ioyes abate,</l>
                  <l>I ſtill may dwell within thy ſacred wall,</l>
                  <l>And that mine eies may ſee thy courts of ſtate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſeeing them I may admire the ſame,</l>
                  <l>That, whilſt my vitall parts draw quickning breath,</l>
                  <l>I may ſing praiſe to God, and laud his name,</l>
                  <l>And naught may end that ſweet conſent but death.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 Then will he hide, and me ſafe-guarded lay</l>
                  <l>Vnder the ſhadow of his ſauing tent,</l>
                  <l>Remou'd from all that might my mind diſmay,</l>
                  <l>In walls as ſtrong as rocks of hard aſcent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 Nor will he leaue me now to be a prey</l>
                  <l>To th'impious force of the ſeditious rout,</l>
                  <l>So conqu'ring I to him my vowes will pay;</l>
                  <l>Who won the field ſhould his name be left out?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 Heare me who call, and proſtrate at thy feet,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:150662:33"/>Broken and bruis'd, as on a rack, with paine,</l>
                  <l>With ſweet conſent let grace and goodneſſe meet,</l>
                  <l>To raiſe and eaſe my tortur'd limmes againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 My mind runnes panting after thee, mine eies</l>
                  <l>Fixt on thine eie, attend thee day by day:</l>
                  <l n="9">9 Hide not thy light, that from thy loue doth riſe,</l>
                  <l>Nor leaue me in the dark to find my way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor in thy rage confound thou me thine owne,</l>
                  <l>Protect the life thy ſeruant owes to thee:</l>
                  <l>O thou the hope of all his helpe alone,</l>
                  <l>From foes defend, and him from dangers free,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 Who neere, and deere, euen he that gaue me breath,</l>
                  <l>And ſhe that bore me doe forſake me quite,</l>
                  <l>But God that leaues not his when neer'ſt to death,</l>
                  <l>Forſoke me not in my deſpairfull'ſt plight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 Teach me thy waies, by whoſe free grace I liue,</l>
                  <l>And guide my ſteps in the faire path of right,</l>
                  <l>That force, nor feare (wherewith my foes haue ſtriue</l>
                  <l>To draw me from thy way) may work their ſpite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 Not leaue thou me obnoxious to the luſt</l>
                  <l>Of impious men, who me of crimes endite,</l>
                  <l>And witneſſe beare in things that are not iuſt,</l>
                  <l>Arm'd to the proofe with lies, the armes of ſpite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="13">13 Conquer'd at laſt with waight of preſſing ills,</l>
                  <l>My minde would faint, but hope of thy good grace,</l>
                  <l>This comfort to my drooping ſpirits inſtills,</l>
                  <l>That after anxious toiles ioy ſhall take place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:150662:34"/>
                  <l>I liuing here with men that draw like aire,</l>
                  <l>The bleſſings of an happy life expect,</l>
                  <l>Then take not thou the foile of foule deſpaire,</l>
                  <l>The Lord will giue thee ſtrength, and will protect</l>
                  <l>And ſtay thy fainting ſoule, as props vphold</l>
                  <l>A craſed houſe. Then fearleſſe ſtand and bold.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XXVIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVOrlds King then ſtarry Orbes more high,</l>
                  <l>My lifes ſupport, ſur'ſt ſhield to ſaue,</l>
                  <l>Heare mildly my requeſt, leſt I</l>
                  <l>Be like a corpſe brought neere the graue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 Milde Father, to my vowes giue eare,</l>
                  <l>When I with teares lift vp my hands</l>
                  <l>To heau'n, where wandring lights appeare,</l>
                  <l>The Temple where thy glory ſtands.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 With lewd men be not I enrol'd,</l>
                  <l>Nor as their mate, Lord, doome thou me,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe tongues are made by'th Sirene mould,</l>
                  <l>And minds with poiſon tainted be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 Let their reward their lewdneſſe ſhow,</l>
                  <l>As bad their worke, euen be their hire,</l>
                  <l>And let them reape, as they did ſow,</l>
                  <l>Paines equall to their lewd deſire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 The wiſe fore-ſight of thy decree</l>
                  <l>(Who do'ſt my head with honour crowne)</l>
                  <l>Keepes not their hands from falſhood free,</l>
                  <l>Nor holds their ſpite-ſwolne ſtomackes downe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:150662:34"/>
                  <l>And therefore ſhall not their long line</l>
                  <l>Of hopeleſſe ofſpring wide extend,</l>
                  <l>Of ſtocke and houſe ſhall be no ſigne,</l>
                  <l>Their fathers pelfe ſhall ſoone haue end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 To thee all-ruling Lord be laud,</l>
                  <l>Who to my prayers faire paſſage yeelds,</l>
                  <l n="7">7 Whoſe ſtrength armes me from force, and fraud,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe hopefull help my ſafety ſhields.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 Hence ioy triumphing in my breſt,</l>
                  <l>My meaſur'd lines thy praiſes ſing,</l>
                  <l>Who guard'ſt thine owne with dangers preſt,</l>
                  <l>And from all ſnares preſeru'ſt thy King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 Thou Prince of men keepe ſafe and ſound</l>
                  <l>Thy people, and let <hi>Hebers</hi> race</l>
                  <l>In all Earths bleſſings ſtill abound,</l>
                  <l>Vntill the night doe leaue his place.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XXIX.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THough rich in gold, though thou in wealth abound,</l>
                  <l>Thy front adorn'd with a victorious crowne,</l>
                  <l>Acknowledge God, nor be ingratefull found,</l>
                  <l>Vſe thy good hap, but know heauen ſent it downe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 Sing praiſe to him, and with ſubmiſſe requeſt</l>
                  <l>Make him thy friend, who made the worlds wide frame,</l>
                  <l>And with his becke who rules the skie addreſt</l>
                  <l>With glittering Starres, giue honour to his name.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Whoſe ſounding voice powres moiſtning ſhowres below,</l>
                  <l>Who horrid tumults raiſing in the skye,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:150662:35"/>With roring thunders makes fierce Boreas blow,</l>
                  <l>And mount the ſwelling waues, when Seas grow high:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 A voice, I ſay, with Maieſty repleate,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe power makes good, what firſt his will deſign'd,</l>
                  <l n="5">5 Whether he pleas'd of Cedars tall and great,</l>
                  <l>T'uncloth the hills, or rend high Elmes with wind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 Or burſt out ſtones, conioyn'd to ſtones with lime,</l>
                  <l>Or toſſe the hills, and their firſt footing change,</l>
                  <l>As youthfull rage ioy'd with the ſpringing time,</l>
                  <l>Doth pricke the luſty Bull to leape and range.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 If his voice ſtrikes fire flaſhes from the cloud,</l>
                  <l n="8">8 The deſert Cabines of th'Arabians ſhake:</l>
                  <l n="9">9 Beaſts quake for feare, abortiues diſauow'd,</l>
                  <l>Burſt forth with paine. Okes fell when he but ſpake.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What Heauen containes in his gold-vaulted roome,</l>
                  <l>What Earth ſuſtaines, ennamel'd with rare skill,</l>
                  <l>And what lies hid within the Seas deepe wombe,</l>
                  <l>They all confeſſe Gods vnreſiſted will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 The ſinne-reuenging ſea, mou'd at his ſound,</l>
                  <l>O'rewhelm'd the Mountaines, when it rag'd and rau'd,</l>
                  <l>And thou (to whoſe decrees are all things bound)</l>
                  <l>Waſt pleas'd to drowne the world, ſo ſinfull made.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 If thou giue ſtrength, we neither feare our foes,</l>
                  <l>Or proud for wealth, or for their number daring:</l>
                  <l>If thou giue peace, from Plenties horne that flowes,</l>
                  <l>No bleſſing ſhall to <hi>Jſ'achs</hi> race be ſparing.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="ode">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:150662:35"/>
               <head>PSAL. XXX.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>OF thee my Muſe, of thee my Harpe ſhall ſound,</l>
                  <l>Iudge of the world, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce all good things do flow,</l>
                  <l>Freed from deaths iawes that ſought my ouerthrow,</l>
                  <l>My vowes now will I pay, by promiſe bound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Releas'd by thee nor now inſults my foe,</l>
                  <l>To ſee mine eyes poure forth their floods of teares,</l>
                  <l>Nor takes delight to ſee me vext with feares</l>
                  <l>Of preſſing ills, thou cool'ſt his courage ſo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 I ſought thy helpe, when I vnſteddy ſtood,</l>
                  <l>And doubtfull of ſucceſſe, to thee did ſue,</l>
                  <l>By thee refreſh'd, alone by thee I drew</l>
                  <l>Th'aires louely light, that cheeres the vitall blood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Nor doe I lye with fates long night oppreſt</l>
                  <l>In the low vaults, where windowes want, and lights;</l>
                  <l n="4">4 But you deuoted to the ſacred rites,</l>
                  <l>And cleane oblations of a purer breſt,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Him let your heart with ſweet harmonious cheere,</l>
                  <l>(Who mindes your prayers) be mindfull to record,</l>
                  <l>Extoll with praiſe your Sire, and Sou'raigne Lord,</l>
                  <l>Since to your vowes he bends his liſtning eare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 The heate of his reuenging ire alayde,</l>
                  <l>Doth vaniſh as a fleeting buble falls,</l>
                  <l>And a ſweet life, which no ſad hap appalls,</l>
                  <l>By his right-hand is to good men repaid.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If late at night our mournfull faces be</l>
                  <l>Bath'd all with teares, yet when the golden Sunne</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:150662:36"/>Sheds forth his beames, the glaſſe of griefe is run,</l>
                  <l>And ſmiling mirth our captiu'd minds ſets free.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 When I had all that fits a bleſſed ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Thus ſaid I to my ſelfe, no guſt nor gall</l>
                  <l>Shall ſtay my courſe ſo fortunate in all,</l>
                  <l>Nor doubtfull chance giue ſweet content the mate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 Thou giuing me ſtrength, wealth, and high degree,</l>
                  <l>And like a mount rais'd with ſtrong walls of braſſe,</l>
                  <l>Strengthning my crowne, Credulity that was</l>
                  <l>My minds Enchantreſſe, fed vaine pride in me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But leauing me vnto my fooliſh vaine,</l>
                  <l>Thou drawing backe thine hand, that light wing'd dame</l>
                  <l>Falſe Fortune fled, and left all out of frame,</l>
                  <l>My houſe diſord'red in the head and traine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 Then preſently, ſole Preſident of all,</l>
                  <l>Humbly my vowes I on thine altar ſtrew'd,</l>
                  <l>I crau'd thine ayd, and ſaid with teares bedew'd,</l>
                  <l n="9">9 What good to thee can of my blood befall?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What vſe canſt thou make of my breathleſſe limmes?</l>
                  <l>Can the cold aſhes that in ſilence lye</l>
                  <l>In Deaths darke manſion thy great works deſcry</l>
                  <l>To th'after-age, and ſing thee ſacred hymnes?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 Milde to my vowes thy facile care apply,</l>
                  <l>That to thy grace doth eaſie paſſage make,</l>
                  <l>Nor from my teares turne thy grim lookes, but take</l>
                  <l>The plague-ſores from my limmes that fretting lye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 When I implore thou doſt thine care addreſſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:150662:36"/>And laiſt it cloſe, and wip'ſt my teares away,</l>
                  <l>And in their place bring'ſt mirth, and to allay</l>
                  <l>My griefe comes ioy, which hand and heart expreſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 Of thee my layes ſhall ſing, my harpe ſhall ſound,</l>
                  <l>My voice on thee deuoted ſhall attend,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall my Muſe want matter to commend,</l>
                  <l>Since of her ſong thy praiſe ſhall be the ground.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XXXI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN thee my hope I plac'd,</l>
                  <l>Who beſt mad'ſt all things good,</l>
                  <l>See I be not diſgrac'd</l>
                  <l>Whilſt hope dies in the bud.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Me iuſt Reuenger free,</l>
                  <l>And from falſe foes exempt:</l>
                  <l n="2">2 Beningly heare thou me,</l>
                  <l>And take me from contempt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Keepe me as in a Rocke,</l>
                  <l>Where no path euer was,</l>
                  <l>Or clos'd where needs no lock,</l>
                  <l>Within a wall of braſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Thou art my rocke ſo ſteepe</l>
                  <l>As none can footing winne,</l>
                  <l>My braſſe-wall trench'd ſo deepe</l>
                  <l>As none can enter in.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So may thy name affright</l>
                  <l>The minds of my proud foes,</l>
                  <l n="4">4 That whilſt thou lead'ſt me right,</l>
                  <l>I may their ſnares diſcloſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:150662:37"/>
                  <l n="5">5 Thou art my ſtrength, with thee</l>
                  <l>I leaue my life in truſt,</l>
                  <l>True of thy word ſaue me,</l>
                  <l>And keepe thy cou'nant iuſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 I hate with all my heart</l>
                  <l>Thoſe that purſue vaine dreames,</l>
                  <l>My ſteddy hope thou art,</l>
                  <l>My hau'n in rougheſt ſtreames.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 When dangers ſore oppreſſe,</l>
                  <l>The cleare light of thy grace</l>
                  <l>Doth griefe ſoone diſpoſſeſſe,</l>
                  <l>And brings ioy in the place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 Vext without right or lawes,</l>
                  <l>Where tyrant rage doth raigne,</l>
                  <l>Thou took'ſt me from his iawes,</l>
                  <l>And didſt pale death reſtraine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 Haue pitty then on him</l>
                  <l>Who all to peeces rent,</l>
                  <l>Mind, eye, and eu'ry limme</l>
                  <l>Is ſenſleſſe, dim, and ſpent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 My fraile life worne with anguiſh</l>
                  <l>Doth ſlide away, with groanes</l>
                  <l>My foiled forces languiſh,</l>
                  <l>And iuiceleſſe are my bones.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 Who hates me takes a pride</l>
                  <l>At my miſhap to jeere,</l>
                  <l>Some flip for feare aſide,</l>
                  <l>And not a friend comes neere.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:150662:37"/>
                  <l n="12">12 Rac'd out of mind, as dead,</l>
                  <l>My Kinne deny me place,</l>
                  <l>Where I was borne and bred</l>
                  <l>No pot ſhard held more baſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="13">13 In troops with publick ſcorne</l>
                  <l>The raſcals me diſdaine,</l>
                  <l>My death a crue hath ſworne,</l>
                  <l>And plot with might and maine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="14">14 But confident the whiles</l>
                  <l>Of helpe from thee, my foes</l>
                  <l>Their threats, wrongs, taunts, and guiles</l>
                  <l>Diſturb not my repoſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="15">15 Of life thou guid'ſt the line,</l>
                  <l>And mak'ſt time ſwift or ſlow,</l>
                  <l>Free me who, Lord, am thine,</l>
                  <l>From rage of my fell foe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="16">16 Ah ſhow thy louely face</l>
                  <l>To me thy ſeruant deare,</l>
                  <l>Still let me find thy grace,</l>
                  <l>As thoſe that doe thee feare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="17">17 Nor let it be my ſhame,</l>
                  <l>That I implore thine aid,</l>
                  <l>Bluſh they are worthy blame,</l>
                  <l>And deepe in ſilence laid</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sleepe they out their long night.</l>
                  <l n="18">18 Dumb be the tongue doth vſe</l>
                  <l>To lye, to barke, and bite,</l>
                  <l>And moſt the beſt abuſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:150662:38"/>
                  <l n="19">19 How great, how many be</l>
                  <l>Thy bleſſings to thy friends,</l>
                  <l>Witneſſe the Poles that ſee,</l>
                  <l>Thine bleſt beyond their ends.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="20">20 Theſe ſafe thy Grace protects,</l>
                  <l>When great men threat and ſwell,</l>
                  <l>No poiſonous tongue infects</l>
                  <l>Thoſe in thy houſe who dwell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="21">21 Eternall be thy grace,</l>
                  <l>The worlds ſupremeſt Guide,</l>
                  <l>Who, as in a ſtrong place,</l>
                  <l>Do'ſt me from danger hide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="22">22 Hopeleſſe, and helpleſſe when</l>
                  <l>I ſcarce was ſau'd by flight,</l>
                  <l>I to my ſelfe ſaid then</l>
                  <l>My God hath left me quite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But hauing me in mind,</l>
                  <l>When ditefull'ſt dangers preſt,</l>
                  <l>Thou lent'ſt thy eare ſo kind</l>
                  <l>When I made my requeſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="23">23 To heau'n your hearts who vow'd,</l>
                  <l>Loue your all-foſtring Sire</l>
                  <l>Who doth depreſſe the proud;</l>
                  <l>And raiſe his followers higher.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="24">24 In God who put their truſt</l>
                  <l>Rely on him in all,</l>
                  <l>Let Chance with no rough guſt</l>
                  <l>Your courages appall.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="ode">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:150662:38"/>
               <head>PSAL. XXXII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THrice bleſſed He whoſe heauenly Fathers grace</l>
                  <l>Remits his ſinnes which kill the liuing ſoule,</l>
                  <l>And whoſe flagitious facts hid from his face</l>
                  <l>He buries deepe, nor puts them in his role.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 Thrice bleſſed he to whom the Iudge of right</l>
                  <l>Imputes not his fraile lifes ſin-ſtraying wayes,</l>
                  <l>Nor in his heart found ſlights conceal'd from light,</l>
                  <l>Such as for ſhame Fraud in her cloſet layes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Whilſt in my breſt I foſtred the diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>My bones diſplac'd, my ioints I ſcarce could draw,</l>
                  <l>And mournfull griefe, that nothing could appeaſe,</l>
                  <l>Cri'd and complain'd, nor could I giue it law.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 With thy ſtrong hand enrag'd thou didſt me preſſe,</l>
                  <l>Both when the night with clouds did hide the day,</l>
                  <l>And when the roſie Sun did him addreſſe</l>
                  <l>To ſhow the world his beames to guide their way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So waſting griefe diſcolour'd had my skin,</l>
                  <l>Paine dri'd my moiſture pin'd with ſad diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>That Cancer, when his furious flames begin</l>
                  <l>To burne the ſand-ſow'd crop, his rage is leſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 Then did I change my mind, and ſhew'd my wound,</l>
                  <l>And laid my follies forth before thy face,</l>
                  <l>Diſclos'd my fraud, then from ſins bonds vnbound,</l>
                  <l>I reconcil'd was taken to thy grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 Who ſeekes to keepe his court of Conſcience ſound,</l>
                  <l>With humble prayer let him appeaſe thine ire,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:150662:39"/>Nor let him feare, though Earth the Seas confound,</l>
                  <l>The threats of direfull rage that burne like fire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 Thou ſtill at hand to helpe, doſt ſet me free</l>
                  <l>From perils which doe fiercely me aſſaile:</l>
                  <l>In all my parts are ioyes infus'd by thee,</l>
                  <l>Like his that breakes his bonds, and ſcapes the gaole.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 Nor leau'ſt thou here: I will, ſaiſt thou, expell</l>
                  <l>The dusky clouds that keepe thy mind from light:</l>
                  <l>The bleſſed way of life I will thee tell,</l>
                  <l>Nor from thy ſteps will I reflect my ſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 Now be not thou like Mule or Horſe, whoſe breſts</l>
                  <l>With brutiſh fury fill'd, doe follow kind,</l>
                  <l>And know no kindneſſe, but aduance their creſts,</l>
                  <l>Till bit and curb doe tame their fiercer mind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 Head-ſtrong iniquity ſhall vndergoe</l>
                  <l>A world of paines, but who ſincerely craue</l>
                  <l>Of God with faith (whoſe grace doth euer flow</l>
                  <l>To thoſe that humbly ſue) ſhall pardon haue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 Who all from Right, and in fee ſimple hold,</l>
                  <l>And who loue Truth, and know nor fraud, nor guile,</l>
                  <l>With geſture, and with voice, your ioyes vnfold,</l>
                  <l>Since gracefull Heau'n doth on you ſweetly ſmile.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XXXIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YOu that chaſte loue to Righteouſneſſe profeſſe,</l>
                  <l>With chearfull layes ſing of the Lord, who made</l>
                  <l>The worlds round ball: 'tis fit your ſongs expreſſe</l>
                  <l>Your loue to Right, who know no other trade.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:150662:39"/>
                  <l n="2">2 Him praiſe with Harpe that yeelds a Siren ſound,</l>
                  <l>And Shalmes with wind that warbling notes diuide:</l>
                  <l>That hand that proues his maſters skill profound</l>
                  <l>On twice fiue ſtrings here let his art be tri'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Let vs to him new ſongs of ioy deuiſe,</l>
                  <l>And him alone ſound with the Trumpets ſhrill,</l>
                  <l n="4">4 On whoſe bare word all faith and truth relyes,</l>
                  <l>And Equity attends his royall will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 For He's the God that Iuſtice loues, and right,</l>
                  <l>And truth; for why? in him no fraud is found,</l>
                  <l>His Bountie's knowne, expos'd to all mens fight,</l>
                  <l>So far as the vaſt Earth hath any bound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 He with his word, (whoſe word is his decree)</l>
                  <l>The ſhining globe of brighter Heau'ns did bend</l>
                  <l>Like to a bow, and ſo the lights we ſee</l>
                  <l>In the flame colour'd skye their beames extend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 He bounds the reſtleſſe Ocean with a ſhore,</l>
                  <l>And curbs his lawleſſe rage begirt about,</l>
                  <l>The waters in a cellar kept for ſtore</l>
                  <l>When he hath cauſe to vſe, he calls them out.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 Him Eaſt and Weſt both ſerue with awfull feare:</l>
                  <l>Who dwels in climes diſcou'red, or vnknowne</l>
                  <l>In th'vtmoſt bounds, where ſea and land appeare,</l>
                  <l>Adore he him as Sou'raigne Lord alone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 What here below drawes breath, or breathleſſe dies,</l>
                  <l>Doth liue and dye euen as he pleaſe to will,</l>
                  <l>Vnder whoſe changeleſſe law all trembling lies,</l>
                  <l>Bound to obey, and his Edicts fulfill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:150662:40"/>
                  <l n="10">10 Who far more wiſe then men profeſſing arts,</l>
                  <l>(Profaner men that vainer arts profeſſe)</l>
                  <l>He mockes the baſer births of their lewd harts,</l>
                  <l>And fruſtrate bad men of all good ſucceſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 But what the Author of all things propounds,</l>
                  <l>And keepes within the cloſet of his mind,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt day and night doe tread their meaſur'd rounds,</l>
                  <l>Shall ſteddy ſtand, nor alteration find.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 Ah thrice, nay more then fourefold bleſt are thoſe</l>
                  <l>Whoſe patrone God takes on himſelfe to be,</l>
                  <l>And whom he tooke peculiarly, and choſe</l>
                  <l>To be his owne in a more neere degree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="13">13 From the ſtar-ſpangled vaults where Saints abide,</l>
                  <l>The Grand-Sire of the world caſts downe his eye,</l>
                  <l n="14">14 And in his inmoſt roomes retir'd aſide,</l>
                  <l>Beholds the cares and toiles wherein men lye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="15">15 Who fram'd the heart, and her darke angles made,</l>
                  <l>And knowes what lurkes in eu'ry humane breſt,</l>
                  <l>There's nothing hid eu'n in the darkeſt ſhade,</l>
                  <l>That can be kept from him, or lye ſuppreſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="16">16 The King in vaine troops with his muſtred bands</l>
                  <l>To be ſafe-guarded, and preſeru'd ſecure;</l>
                  <l>The Souldier hopes in vaine with his ſteel'd hands</l>
                  <l>Againſt his foe to be protected ſure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="17">17 Oft-times the Horſe that ouer-runs the winde</l>
                  <l>Deceiues his rider, nor performes his ſpeed,</l>
                  <l n="18">18 But God beholds Iuſt men of heauenly kinde</l>
                  <l>With a fixte ye that ſtill his marke doth heed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:150662:40"/>
                  <l n="19">19 And doth retort the darts of daring fate,</l>
                  <l>And ſtops the iawes of hunger ſharpe and fell:</l>
                  <l n="20">20 Hence comes our hope of helpe, and happy ſtate,</l>
                  <l>None can like him, and none will guard ſo well.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="21">21 And hearts deuoted to his ſeruice, He</l>
                  <l>Beſprinkles all with oile of ioy, and brings</l>
                  <l n="22">22 Their hopes, and vowes, that on him fixed be,</l>
                  <l>To happy end, whence endleſſe ſolace ſprings.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XXXIV.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN weale, or woe, what e're befall,</l>
                  <l>At all times I the Lord will praiſe,</l>
                  <l>My mouth with high-ſtrain'd accents ſhall</l>
                  <l>His praiſe reſound, and alwaies raiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 This ſhall my ioy and comfort be,</l>
                  <l>And preſent eaſe in dire diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>The mournfull crue thus following me,</l>
                  <l>Shall cauſe their ſorrow ſeeme the leſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Thus all in one, let vs purſue</l>
                  <l>With praiſe his name and ſou'raigne might.</l>
                  <l n="4">4 In dangers when I call'd, he knew</l>
                  <l>My voice, and ſoone put feare to flight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 Who heart and all to him apply,</l>
                  <l>With cheerfull hue their viſage ſhines,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhame with her cheek-ſtaining dye,</l>
                  <l>Shall ſhew them croſt in their deſignes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 Behold this poore penurious wretch</l>
                  <l>When he to him for aide did call,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:150662:41"/>He forth his ſauing arme did ſtretch,</l>
                  <l>And freed him from what ill might fall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 Who feare the Lord an Angell ſent</l>
                  <l>Doth guard their camps, and fence them ſo,</l>
                  <l>That impious force againſt them bent,</l>
                  <l>He foiles them all, leaues not a foe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 Make proofe, and you ſhall quickly ſee</l>
                  <l>How far Gods bounty doth extend,</l>
                  <l>And know how bleſt they onely be,</l>
                  <l>Who hope, and hap to him commend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 You holy Nations ſerue the Lord,</l>
                  <l>They nothing want who him adore.</l>
                  <l n="10">10 Extortious wrongs doe not afford</l>
                  <l>Their maſters food, when theſe haue ſtore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 Come heauens delight, attend, and heare,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt I the Lords true feare relate:</l>
                  <l n="12">12 Who look'ſt for life from dangers cleare,</l>
                  <l>And for long daies in happy ſtate,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="13">13 Refraine thy tongue from poiſonous ſpite,</l>
                  <l>And keepe thy lips from curſed fraud,</l>
                  <l n="14">14 Auoid the crooked waies; doe right,</l>
                  <l>And loue ſweet reſt, and peace applaud.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="15">15 The Lord beholds the innocent,</l>
                  <l>And to their vowes lends open eare,</l>
                  <l n="16">16 His brow againſt the wicked bent,</l>
                  <l>Their names in no records appeare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="17">17 The Lord attends the iuſt mans plaint,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:150662:41"/>And frees him from all preſſing ills,</l>
                  <l n="18">18 When others with loſt labour faint,</l>
                  <l>And hopeleſſe are to worke their wills.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And when the minde with griefes oppreſt</l>
                  <l>Doth vnderlye the waight it beares,</l>
                  <l>Gods helpe at hand is ſtill addreſt,</l>
                  <l>And care-diſtracted ſoules vp-reares.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="19">19 What good men would blinde Chance enuies,</l>
                  <l>And taskes them to laborious toiles,</l>
                  <l>But God, who guards the godly wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Abates her edge, and forces foiles.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="20 21">20, 21 And keepes the bones in their right place</l>
                  <l>Vnbroken by the hands of foes,</l>
                  <l>When lewd men (to their more diſgrace)</l>
                  <l>By their owne ſinnes worke their owne woes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And he who's not the godlies friend,</l>
                  <l>Shall with his houſe quite ruin'd fall,</l>
                  <l n="22">22 But who ſerues God, he doth defend</l>
                  <l>His life, houſe, liuelihood, and all.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XXXV.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BLeſt Architect, who mad'ſt the worlds wide frame,</l>
                  <l>Come and protect me, and my cauſe defend,</l>
                  <l>And to my foes with ignominious ſhame</l>
                  <l>Retort the ill which they tow'rds me intend.</l>
                  <l n="2 3">2, 3 Take with thy darts thy all-reſiſting ſhield,</l>
                  <l>And draw thy ſword, and meet my foes i'th field.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Say to my ſoule, ſecured by mine aid</l>
                  <l>Let not thy courage be appall'd with feare,</l>
                  <l n="4">
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:150662:42"/>4 The ſhamefull bluſh that ſhowes a ſhind diſmaid</l>
                  <l>Be that the colour, and let that appeare</l>
                  <l>In my foes front, and turne they ſoone their backe,</l>
                  <l>Who their blind traps prepar'd to work my wracke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 As Boreas fierce doth whirle the duſt about,</l>
                  <l>So let the wreakfull Angell in their flight</l>
                  <l n="6">6 Hard at the heeles purſue this heartleſſe rout</l>
                  <l>Dabling in durt, let then the ſullen night</l>
                  <l>Cloud all her lampes, that frighted with her frowne,</l>
                  <l>The wreakfull Angell then may ding them downe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 For ſince they ſought by their lewd luring traines,</l>
                  <l>To take me in their nets who meant but good,</l>
                  <l>And digg'd a pit in th'Earths deepe hollow veines,</l>
                  <l n="8">8 Snar'd be they in the nets laid for my blood,</l>
                  <l>And where my death was threatned, in that pit</l>
                  <l>Headlong fall they, and blindfold lye in it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 In the meane time my heart ſhall leape withall,</l>
                  <l>All ſweet delight infus'd. My mind now free</l>
                  <l>By grant of grace from harmes that might befall,</l>
                  <l>Shall praiſe the Lord, whence comfort comes to me;</l>
                  <l n="10">10 And all the ſenſes that expreſſe the mind,</l>
                  <l>Shall cry, and ſay, None like our God we find,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who guards the poore from violence of thoſe</l>
                  <l>That preſſe them down with their huge waight of pride,</l>
                  <l>And whoſe reuenging hand keepes off the blowes</l>
                  <l>That would confound, were he not on their ſide.</l>
                  <l n="11">11 Conſpiring Calumny doth ſpit her ſpite,</l>
                  <l>And of foule crimes me guiltleſſe doth endite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 They feigne flagitious facts which I ne're knew,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:150662:42"/>To bring my ſoule vnto a ſhamefull end.</l>
                  <l>What I did well with malice they purſue,</l>
                  <l>And breake their ſleepes whilſt they my death intend.</l>
                  <l n="13">13 Whilſt poiſ'nous griefe burnes like a plaguy ſore,</l>
                  <l>And eats their intrails, in ill caſe before,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I in a ſable hue, and mourning weed,</l>
                  <l>Deform'd, and worne, ſcourg'd with pale famines rod,</l>
                  <l>Groueling on ground, eyes, hand, and heart agree'd,</l>
                  <l>With teares and humble ſute t'appeaſe my God.</l>
                  <l n="14">14 So friend for friend, ſo brother mourns for brother,</l>
                  <l>So ſons bedew with teares their deare dead mother.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="15">15 If Fortune toucht me with her heauy hand,</l>
                  <l>They flock, and ioy at my ſuppoſed ills,</l>
                  <l>The raſcall rout, when I thinke nothing, band</l>
                  <l>To worke on me their proud and ſpitefull wills.</l>
                  <l n="16">16 Baſe Paraſites, and all the babling crue,</l>
                  <l>Whet tooth on tooth, and their fell poiſon ſpue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="17">17 O Father deare when ſhall this long forbaring,</l>
                  <l>And irkſome patience haue a finall end?</l>
                  <l>Reſtraine this ſcoffing pride, and ſaucy daring,</l>
                  <l>And me thus left let not fierce Lyons rend:</l>
                  <l n="18">18 That this by thee I may acknowledge done,</l>
                  <l>That now I liue, and ſee the louely Sunne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And in the ſolemne meetings I will ſing</l>
                  <l>Of Thee, and of thy ready helpe to thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who call on thee, the vniuerſall King.</l>
                  <l n="19">19 Nor let the crue which fat and fulſome growes</l>
                  <l>By laughing at mine ills, to ſee me pin'd,</l>
                  <l>Nouriſh vaine hopes of wrongs which they deſign'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:150662:43"/>
                  <l>With nods and winkes let not my cruell foe</l>
                  <l>Note me, nor triumph at my bad ſucceſſe,</l>
                  <l n="20">20 Who ſtill inſults with ſcornfull words that flow</l>
                  <l>From his fell gall, and ill-aduis'd doth preſſe</l>
                  <l>On me with traines (that faine would liue at reſt)</l>
                  <l>To ſnare me ſleeping, by his guiles oppreſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="21">21 They girne and fleere, and, Ha, ſay they, our eyes,</l>
                  <l>Our eyes haue ſeene this ſmiling ſun-ſhine day.</l>
                  <l n="22">22 Who view'ſt with thy all-ſeeing lampes what lies</l>
                  <l>In the wide world diſperſt, canſt thou yet ſtay,</l>
                  <l>And ſee, ſee this? Then ſetting all aſide,</l>
                  <l>Protect thou me. Delay drawes on their pride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="23">23 Vp, vp at length with thy reuenging hand</l>
                  <l>Batter and bruiſe the refractary proud:</l>
                  <l n="24">24 And thou iuſt Iudge with iuſt reuenge withſtand</l>
                  <l>Lewd mens attempts, that will not elſe be bow'd,</l>
                  <l>Nor let them beare, as they had wonne a prize,</l>
                  <l>Mirth in their mindes, when teares are in mine eies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="25">25 Nor let them mutter in their inward ſoule,</l>
                  <l>Ha, ha, all now goes right, and farre beyond</l>
                  <l>Our hopefull plots, now haue we wonne the goale,</l>
                  <l>See where he lies, whoſe hopes were vaine and fond.</l>
                  <l n="26">26 Let them repay with ignominious ſhame</l>
                  <l>Their fooliſh mirth, and pride that mou'd the ſame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And let the bluſhing hue, which ſhame attends,</l>
                  <l>Repell the ioyes vnſeaſonably bred</l>
                  <l>Within their breſts, to ſee me miſſe my ends.</l>
                  <l n="27">27 But who are with another ſpirit led,</l>
                  <l>And take to heart to ſee me walke vpright,</l>
                  <l>Vſher'd by Conſcience that no feares afright,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:150662:43"/>
                  <l>Liue they a life from ſorrow far remote</l>
                  <l>In ſweet repoſe, and raiſe vnto the skye</l>
                  <l>Their Sou'raignes praiſe, ſtrain'd to the higheſt note,</l>
                  <l>Who frees from cares thoſe that on him rely.</l>
                  <l n="28">28 Bleſt Sauiour of mankind, let my tongue ſing</l>
                  <l>Thy Iuſtice alwaies, whence all right doth ſpring,</l>
                  <l>And tell thy Grace, which guides the ruling raines,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt in my breſt one ſparke of heate remaines.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XXXVI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ALthough thou burne in ſacred flames</l>
                  <l>The intrailes of a thouſand Cowes,</l>
                  <l>Kiſſe ſtockes and ſtones, with hallow'd names,</l>
                  <l>And mumble double praiers and vowes,</l>
                  <l>And heape thine Altars all beſet</l>
                  <l>With the beſt gifts that thou canſt get.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I will not yet thinke thee a jot</l>
                  <l>The more religious for all that,</l>
                  <l>Since that thy ſins ſay thou art not,</l>
                  <l>And all thou do'ſt denyeth flat</l>
                  <l>There is a God that rules at all</l>
                  <l>With prouidence this our round ball.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 How plauſible ſoe're thou ſeeme</l>
                  <l>And faire in ſhow aboue the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Yet all may ſee, and ſeeing deeme</l>
                  <l>Foule ſinne lyes cloſe couch'd in thy breſt,</l>
                  <l>And burſting forth like fire brings hate,</l>
                  <l>Which followes thee with ſhame her mate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Whate're thou ſaiſt is guilt with guile,</l>
                  <l>With thankleſſe cares thou putteſt by</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:150662:44"/>All wholeſome words, and others while</l>
                  <l>They wiſh thy good, thou think'ſt they lye:</l>
                  <l n="4">4 Contriuing miſchiefe all night long,</l>
                  <l>Thou fly'ſt from right, and foſtreſt wrong.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 Great ruler of the world, the land,</l>
                  <l>The ſea and sky thee gracious find,</l>
                  <l>And all that heauen enfolds, doth ſtand</l>
                  <l>And fall to thee, all in their kind.</l>
                  <l n="6">6 Thy rule of right and ſacred skill,</l>
                  <l>As it made all, ſo guides all ſtill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It higher is then tops of hils</l>
                  <l>Whereon the ſnow doth longeſt lye,</l>
                  <l>Deeper then gulfes that nothing fills,</l>
                  <l>Hence men draw breath, and liue thereby:</l>
                  <l>Nor ſcape thy care the beaſts on earth,</l>
                  <l>Nor creeping things of loweſt birth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 In this all comforts that we haue</l>
                  <l>Of life, and liuelihood are found,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt the pure ſoule is made a ſlaue</l>
                  <l>Here in the bodies dungeon bound.</l>
                  <l>As birds by dammes ſafe brooded lye,</l>
                  <l>So by thine aid all harmes we flye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 But when the exil'd mind is free</l>
                  <l>By death, and goes from whence it came,</l>
                  <l>Where all the roomes ſtar-ſpangled be,</l>
                  <l>There want, and with her griefe, and ſhame</l>
                  <l>Are baniſh'd; there hath eu'ry man</l>
                  <l>More then he wiſh'd, wiſh what he can.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There pleaſures are ſtrew'd all about,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:150662:44"/>And vnmixt ioyes doe there abound,</l>
                  <l>There like a torrent guſheth out</l>
                  <l>Streames of delights not elſewhere found.</l>
                  <l n="9">9 Thence ſprings the life whoſe fount ſtill flowes,</l>
                  <l>The life which Deaths fithe neuer mowes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There vaniſh miſts that darke our minds,</l>
                  <l>And like to clouds doe blind our hearts,</l>
                  <l>But from thy face the beame that findes</l>
                  <l>His radiant light, vs light imparts;</l>
                  <l>Which ſhall with knowledge feed the mind,</l>
                  <l>That leaues no dregs of filth behind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 Thoſe with thy gracious goodneſſe cheere</l>
                  <l>Who know thee, and what thou haſt done,</l>
                  <l>And loue the truth, to thee ſo deare,</l>
                  <l>With heart and mind cleare as the Sun,</l>
                  <l>Let, let them now in iuſtice haue</l>
                  <l>The bleſſings which thy Grace firſt gaue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 Nor let the foot of ſurly pride</l>
                  <l>Trample on me, nor let the rout</l>
                  <l>Of impious men put me beſide</l>
                  <l>My houſe, and home, and thruſt me out.</l>
                  <l n="12">12 Who ioy in ſin be ſin their fall,</l>
                  <l>That they once downe, riſe not at all.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XXXVII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AH let not Spite enflame thy gall,</l>
                  <l>Though fortunate thou lewd men find,</l>
                  <l>Nor at their wealth fret thou at all,</l>
                  <l>More fugitiue then is the wind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:150662:45"/>
                  <l n="2">2 So fades their ſhadow of renowne,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeming ſhow of happy ſtate,</l>
                  <l>As graſſe in flowry meades cut downe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe leaues their verdure ſoone abate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 Truſt thou in God, with heart and hand</l>
                  <l>Purſue the trade of right, and truth,</l>
                  <l>So will he giue thee houſe and land,</l>
                  <l>And feed thy age, who nurſt thy youth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 Rapt be thy ſoule with his delight,</l>
                  <l>And of thy ioy be he the baſe,</l>
                  <l>So cheer'd and cheriſht day and night,</l>
                  <l>He'll crowne thy wiſhes with his grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 Commit thy life, goods, and good name</l>
                  <l>To his alone directing hand,</l>
                  <l>Then as thy ſelfe would'ſt haue the ſame,</l>
                  <l>Thy hope and hap ſhall iointly ſtand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 Like heau'ns great light when it doth riſe,</l>
                  <l>Thy Iuſtice he will make appeare,</l>
                  <l>Thy Iudgement too in all mens eyes</l>
                  <l>Like beames at mid-day ſhall be cleare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 Beare thou the croſſes that may fall,</l>
                  <l>And if thou ſee (which few can brooke)</l>
                  <l>The wicked with their pride ſway all,</l>
                  <l>Yet caſt not thou a lowring looke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="8">8 Reſtraine the current of thine ire,</l>
                  <l>And let not hurtfull paſſion in,</l>
                  <l>Leſt emulation moue deſire</l>
                  <l>To run the common courſe of ſin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:150662:45"/>
                  <l n="9">9 Vngodly men ſhall neuer ſtand,</l>
                  <l>But paſſe as ſmoake with ayrie wings,</l>
                  <l>When godly men poſſeſſe the land,</l>
                  <l>Left to their ſeed that after ſprings.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 Stay but a while and thou ſhalt ſee</l>
                  <l>The wicked man conſum'd and gone,</l>
                  <l>His towres of pride ſhall ruin'd be,</l>
                  <l>And no ſigne left to gaze vpon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 The golden meane in humble mind,</l>
                  <l>Shall bleſſe the meeke with peace and reſt,</l>
                  <l>And leaue his well-got lands behind,</l>
                  <l>Of rightfull heires to be poſſeſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 The graceleſſe man doth ſpread his net</l>
                  <l>The good with cunning to enſnare,</l>
                  <l>And his enuenom'd tuſhes whet,</l>
                  <l>Chaf'd with deſpight, and fretfull care.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="13">13 But God beholds this from his throne,</l>
                  <l>And laughes to ſcorne theſe threats ſo vaine,</l>
                  <l>For he fore-ſees he ſoone muſt groane</l>
                  <l>Vpon the rack of tort'ring paine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="14">14 The wicked man doth draw his ſword,</l>
                  <l>And bends his bow to take his marke</l>
                  <l>At him who's iuſt in deed and word</l>
                  <l>The humble Deere in Gods owne parke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="15">15 But his drawne ſword with edge reuers'd</l>
                  <l>Shall wound his maſter with the blow,</l>
                  <l>His ſhaft in vaine made to haue pierc'd,</l>
                  <l>Shall breake aſunder with his bow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:150662:46"/>
                  <l n="16">16 Plaine homely ſtuffe falne to thy lot</l>
                  <l>By a faire courſe ſhall grace thee more,</l>
                  <l>Then all the lothed ſpoiles ill-got</l>
                  <l>By rich men pillaging the poore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="17">17 Extortious goods the Iudge of right</l>
                  <l>Shall ſcatter wide, and bring to duſt</l>
                  <l>The mountaines of theſe men of might,</l>
                  <l>And with his right hand guard the iuſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="18">18 God foſters thoſe who harmleſſe be,</l>
                  <l>And what they haue his grace aſſures,</l>
                  <l>Their birth-right too by his decree</l>
                  <l>Beyond the date of daies endures.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="19">19 When plaguy boiles, and furious armes</l>
                  <l>Doe all the world with rage infeſt,</l>
                  <l>Then he whoſe hand is free from harmes,</l>
                  <l>Shall not with pining dearth be preſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="20">20 But impious men 'gainſt heauen that fight,</l>
                  <l>Shall periſh quite without delay,</l>
                  <l>And vaniſh in the ſmoke ſo light,</l>
                  <l>As fat of Lambes that melt away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="21">21 Vnrighteous men nor giue, nor lend,</l>
                  <l>But borrow, and not pay againe,</l>
                  <l>When frugally the luſt doe ſpend</l>
                  <l>And portions for the poore retaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="22">22 The Iuſt mans friends ſhall free diſpoſe</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſſions to their hopefull breed,</l>
                  <l>When as the ſeed of his proud foes</l>
                  <l>Shall want a root the ſtock to feed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:150662:46"/>
                  <l n="23">23 The Lord loues Iuſt men, and ſuſtaines</l>
                  <l>Their ſteps in all the wayes of right,</l>
                  <l n="24">24 His right hand them from ſlips reſtraines,</l>
                  <l>And if they fall they fall not quite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="25">25 I was a childe, now aged growne,</l>
                  <l>Yet neuer ſaw in all this ſpace</l>
                  <l>The iuſt man left, nor his haue knowne</l>
                  <l>To beg their bread from place to place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="26">26 The righteous man in time of need</l>
                  <l>Vnto the poore doth lend, and giue,</l>
                  <l>Yet leaues to them that ſhall ſucceed</l>
                  <l>Enough whereby they richly liue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="27">27 Eſchew the wrong and winding waies,</l>
                  <l>And follow right as heauen ſhall guide,</l>
                  <l>So whilſt the Sunne with golden rayes</l>
                  <l>Directs the day, thine ſhall abide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="28">28 The Lord takes truth and right to heart,</l>
                  <l>And neuer honeſt men forſakes,</l>
                  <l>But they that from his wayes depart,</l>
                  <l>Their fruitleſſe ſeed no rooting takes,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="29">29 The Iuſt man that is faire poſſeſt</l>
                  <l>Of lands, of goods, of hoofe, or horne,</l>
                  <l>Both he and his ſhall ſee it bleſt,</l>
                  <l>While day and night haue euen and morne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="30">30 Wiſedome and Truth doe ſtill abide</l>
                  <l>Within the lips of honeſt men,</l>
                  <l n="31">31 And heauens iuſt lawes in heart reſide</l>
                  <l>To keepe their feet from Errours denne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:150662:47"/>
                  <l n="32">32 When impious men watch very neere,</l>
                  <l>To bring the iuſt man to his end,</l>
                  <l n="33">33 Then God who ſees his cauſe is cleare,</l>
                  <l>From vniuſt doome will him defend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="34">34 Hope thou in God, his lawes enſue,</l>
                  <l>Then great in wealth, and high in place</l>
                  <l>Hee'll giue thee helpe, and health to view</l>
                  <l>Thy foes to fall before thy face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="35">35 I ſaw great men as freſh and tall</l>
                  <l>As bayes that growes by'th riuer ride,</l>
                  <l>Who whilſt they will, or would haue all,</l>
                  <l>Goe ſtrouting out with ſwelling pride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="36">36 I turn'd my eye, and loe the ſhape</l>
                  <l>And ſubſtance gone of all their glory,</l>
                  <l>Their boundleſſe pow'r which naught could ſcape,</l>
                  <l>Left but their fall to tell their ſtory.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="37">37 Behold the ſtate, and ſtately traine</l>
                  <l>Of men vpright, whoſe lowly mind,</l>
                  <l>Crown'd with content endures no paine,</l>
                  <l>And in old age ſweet quiet find.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="38">38 But factious men for miſchiefe preſt,</l>
                  <l>Their glaſſe ſoone's run, and pleaſure paſt,</l>
                  <l>An end which ſuites with all the reſt</l>
                  <l>Concludes their loathed life at laſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="39">39 The iuſt man caſts his anchor deepe</l>
                  <l>Of ſolid Hope in heau'n aboue,</l>
                  <l>Which ſteddy doth the righteous keepe,</l>
                  <l>That earth nor hell can him remoue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:150662:47"/>
                  <l n="40">40 The Lord giues aid to thoſe that craue,</l>
                  <l>And from all harmes he ſets them cleare,</l>
                  <l>Who him entruſt with all they haue,</l>
                  <l>What man can doe they need not feare.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XXXVIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>COrrect me not, Lord, in thy burning ire,</l>
                  <l>(Who mad'ſt and rul'ſt the vniuerſall maſſe)</l>
                  <l>Though I deſerue what Iuſtice may require,</l>
                  <l>Yet let not Fury on my Iudgement paſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 The arrowes deepe within my entrailes ſticke,</l>
                  <l>Which thy right hand did leuell at my heart,</l>
                  <l>Thy wrath ſo gaules, my conſcience ſo doth pricke,</l>
                  <l>(And forc'd by them feare ſeizeth eu'ry part,)</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="3">3 That in my wounded ſoule no peece is free</l>
                  <l>From mortall ſins, which ſo waſte all within,</l>
                  <l>As that my bones (their ioints ſo looſened be)</l>
                  <l>Haue ſuckt the poiſon of infecting ſin:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 Of ſin that doth ingulfe me in the maine,</l>
                  <l>And if my head aboue the waues but peepe,</l>
                  <l>Or that I doe but ſtriue to riſe againe,</l>
                  <l>It weighes me like a ſtone downe to the deepe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 The new skinn'd skarres of my old wounds renew'd,</l>
                  <l>Spue out foule matter, and with paine brought low,</l>
                  <l n="6">6 With anguiſh, and long lying vglie hu'd,</l>
                  <l>The worſt, and laſt of ills, ſurcharge my woe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 The plague-fore hid within my belly boiles,</l>
                  <l>Nor any part without is free from paine,</l>
                  <l n="8">
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:150662:48"/>8 So weake am I, and broken too with toiles,</l>
                  <l>That day and night I am enforc'd to plaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And made to yeeld vnto my preſſing ills</l>
                  <l>My heart doth cry, and like a Lion roare,</l>
                  <l n="9">9 Thou Monarch of the world, whoſe power all fils,</l>
                  <l>Know'ſt what my ſoule deſires, and ſighes implore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="10">10 My trembling heart, and troubled mind with feare</l>
                  <l>Doe beat, and pant, the iuice, that all parts fed,</l>
                  <l>And vigour ſpent, no force is left to cheare</l>
                  <l>My members ſtricken with a palſie dead.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My eyes now drawing tow'rds their euening, cloud.</l>
                  <l n="11">11 Neere neighbors, &amp; deere friends, &amp; neerer bound</l>
                  <l>By deerer linke of blood, me diſauow'd,</l>
                  <l>And all cry'd faugh, lothing my parts vnſound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 But that proud crue ſtill ready for my ill,</l>
                  <l>Deuiſing wrong with vtmoſt maine, and might,</l>
                  <l>Spread their ſlye nets, and that they hold on ſtill,</l>
                  <l>And impious fraud aſſaid they day and night.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="13 14">13, 14 In the meane while like him was deafe &amp; mute,</l>
                  <l>I ſtone-ſtill ſtood, and ſilence kept as one</l>
                  <l>Who wanted words, and reaſons to confute</l>
                  <l>Obiected crimes, and could reply to none.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="15">15 Whoſe power rules all, O guide me with thy grace,</l>
                  <l n="16">16 In thee my hope is fixt, then let not pride</l>
                  <l>With ſcorne inſult to ſee my dolefull caſe,</l>
                  <l>Or foes triumph if foot but ſlip aſide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="17">17 I ready am thy ſturdy ſtroaks to beare</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:150662:48"/>My skin ſwels with the markes ſtill black and blue,</l>
                  <l>Rent as a plow ſhare doth the furrowes teare,</l>
                  <l>So in long ſtreakes it ſhewes a bloody hue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="18">18 My ſins I know deſerue, deſerue the wound,</l>
                  <l>And worthily I all theſe plagues ſuſtaine,</l>
                  <l n="19">19 But ſtill my foe, my cruell foe gets ground,</l>
                  <l>The faction too doth ſtrength and courage gaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="20">20 They liue, and liuing ſprout, and beare vp head,</l>
                  <l>And though of them I, Lord, deſerue no ill,</l>
                  <l>With wrongs they me purſue, by fury lead,</l>
                  <l>And iniuries repay for my good will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſtill they ſpit their gall, and wot you why?</l>
                  <l>Becauſe I alwayes follow that is right.</l>
                  <l n="21">21 But be not thou far off, nor let me lye,</l>
                  <l>Nor leaue me thus engag'd to ſpitefull'ſt ſpite.</l>
                  <l n="22">22 Make haſt, and giue me thy ſweet ſauing hand,</l>
                  <l>Since for my helpe, I haue but thee to ſtand.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XXXIX.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHen my fell foe triumphing at my harme,</l>
                  <l>Prouok'd me with tart taunts, I in my mind</l>
                  <l>Reſolu'd from biting tearmes my tongue to charme,</l>
                  <l>And brawling ſhun, and all of that baſe kind.</l>
                  <l n="2">2 I lock'd my lips, and rein'd my tongue ſo hard,</l>
                  <l>As not a word could ſcape, all was ſo barr'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But leſt my mouth might raſhly ſpit her gall,</l>
                  <l>I let not paſſe euen words were good and kind,</l>
                  <l n="3">3 But griefe, like fire, finding no vent at all,</l>
                  <l>To burne within the more did fuell find,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:150662:49"/>And rage at laſt, that burſt the curbing reines,</l>
                  <l>Thus on the Lord ſhe calls, and thus complaines:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="4">4 Shew, ſhew what bounds thou to my daies haſt ſet?</l>
                  <l>When ſhall I flye, and from this dungeon free</l>
                  <l>Be rid of loathſome cares, that inly fret?</l>
                  <l n="5">5 Thou liu'ſt paſt date, there is no end with thee,</l>
                  <l>Bleſt of thy ſelfe, and of thy ſelfe moſt ſtrong;</l>
                  <l>But ſoone our glaſſe is run, we liue not long,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 And almoſt leſſe then nothing are our yeares,</l>
                  <l>Like to a flitting ſhade, or breathleſſe ſhape</l>
                  <l>Which in the ſurface of a glaſſe appeares,</l>
                  <l>Nor that can vaine and anxious cares eſcape:</l>
                  <l>Luſt rackes the mind, and ioy doth raiſe his creſt,</l>
                  <l>Hope mounts him vp, by feare againe depreſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We tumults raiſe, and ſpend we know not how,</l>
                  <l>(Without aduiſe not looking to the maine)</l>
                  <l>Our life in things, which folly may auow,</l>
                  <l>But of no moment, fruitleſſe are, and vaine:</l>
                  <l>So whiles we toile, and moile, abroad, at home,</l>
                  <l>We gather wealth apace, God knowes for whom.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 On which ſide ſhall I turne? who giues me ayd,</l>
                  <l>Toſt, and garboild? who frees me wrapt in woes?</l>
                  <l n="8">8 In thee is all my hope. Stop vndelaid</l>
                  <l>This ſinke of ſinne whence all this miſchiefe flowes,</l>
                  <l>And leaue me not to impious follies ſcorne,</l>
                  <l>Launc'd with their ſcoffes and taunts not to be born.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="9">9 I held my peace, when I perceiu'd theſe ills</l>
                  <l>Of thy fierce wrath for ſin reuengers were,</l>
                  <l n="10">10 Who mad'ſt mankind, and guid'ſt their waies, &amp; wils,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:150662:49"/>Thy laſhes yet a little while forbeare,</l>
                  <l>Since ſtrength doth faile, nor doth my life ſuffice</l>
                  <l>To beare the growing paines that ſtill ariſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 When as thy plagues purſue our fretting ſin,</l>
                  <l>Soone ſtrength and beauty fade, and flit away,</l>
                  <l>As Mothes eate cloth when once they are got in.</l>
                  <l>O, man's a fraile and brittle peece of clay.</l>
                  <l n="12">12 Yet to my prayers thy eares, mild Father lend,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſcorne the words which to thy throane I ſend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Turne not thy face from his bedewed eies,</l>
                  <l>That liues a pilgrime, and a wandring gueſt,</l>
                  <l>Nor I, nor had my parents in like wiſe</l>
                  <l>A ſtaid place here, where we our foot might reſt:</l>
                  <l>But day by day, and eu'ry moment vext,</l>
                  <l>We ſpent our ſhort liues in long cares perplext.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="13">13 Then for a while forbeare thy ſharper hand,</l>
                  <l>That I afreſh my fainting breath may draw,</l>
                  <l>Before that I at Deaths broad gates doe ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Where entring once, there's no returne in law:</l>
                  <l>For if he take neuer ſo little hold</l>
                  <l>There's no redemption, goe muſt young and old.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XL.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHen fear &amp; threats about me bellow'd rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
                  <l>And cruell Death ſhook his deuouring dart,</l>
                  <l>Yet Hope from Heauen, though late, at laſt I found,</l>
                  <l>Which ſwag'd chill cares lay trembling at my heart.</l>
                  <l n="2">2 The Lord perceiu'd, and from the gulfe me took,</l>
                  <l>Nor in the mire o're head and eares forſooke;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But on the tops of ſolid rockes he plac'd,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:150662:50"/>And ſhew'd me a faire way where I ſhould goe,</l>
                  <l n="3">3 And in my breſt (with ruines all defac'd)</l>
                  <l>Inſpir'd new breath, and did new matter ſhow,</l>
                  <l>That I might ſing his praiſe on ſweet tun'd ſtrings,</l>
                  <l>In numbers ſmooth which no harſh diſcord brings.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let them ſee this, who all euents impute</l>
                  <l>To whirling Chance, or furious force of Fate,</l>
                  <l>And let them trembling when they haue a ſute</l>
                  <l>Reſt on that Lord who keepes in heauen his ſtate:</l>
                  <l n="4">4 Thrice happy he who caſts his lookes on high,</l>
                  <l>That Faith and Hope may on the Lord rely.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And bleſſed he whom pompe of ſwelling pride</l>
                  <l>Leades not along with her alluring traines,</l>
                  <l>Nor drawes the mind with ſeeming good aſide.</l>
                  <l n="5">5 But, ſacred Sire, how many a pledge remaines</l>
                  <l>Of thy great care to vs, which our weake ſight</l>
                  <l>Sees not, nor tongue their number can recite?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 Thou pluck'ſt me cloſely by the eare, and tells</l>
                  <l>That neither gold buyes out the guilt of ſin,</l>
                  <l>Nor blood of harmleſſe beaſts the ſame repels,</l>
                  <l>Nor Holocauſts can clenſe our crimes within:</l>
                  <l>Since then of me thou, Lord, ſeek'ſt no ſuch thing,</l>
                  <l>But from thy Grace thy fauours freely ſpring.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 I come, ſaid I, command thou me, and ſpare not,</l>
                  <l>Here, ſacred Sire, to doe thy will I ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Reueal'd in Volumes which the lewdeſt dare not</l>
                  <l>Or taxe with nouelty, or errour brand:</l>
                  <l>My mind to this, to this my ſtudy bends,</l>
                  <l>(Which is my firſt, all elſe are ſecond ends)</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:150662:50"/>
                  <l n="8">8 That what I doe, or ſay, or keepe in mind,</l>
                  <l>I may conforme all to thy ſacred bent,</l>
                  <l>For in my heart deepe graued thou maiſt find</l>
                  <l>Thy ſacred Law that ſhewes thy wills extent.</l>
                  <l n="9">9 I preach abroad to Nations far and wide</l>
                  <l>Thy Iuſtice ſo renown'd, ſo often tride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor ſhall my lips take reſt, nor tongue lye ſtill,</l>
                  <l>But ſhall thy mercy and thy iuſtice tell,</l>
                  <l>And with thy name all Nations will I fill,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſeeſt it, Lord, and know'ſt it too right well,</l>
                  <l n="10">10 For I conceal'd not thy iuſt rage to ſin,</l>
                  <l>Nor to the poore how good thou ſtill haſt bin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By my report thy goodneſſe is made knowne</l>
                  <l>To all the lands abroad, thy truth withall,</l>
                  <l n="11">11 Then let thy goodneſſe, and thy faith, which none</l>
                  <l>Found euer yet to faile, or ſhort to fall,</l>
                  <l>Saue me beſet with troopes of miſchiefe round,</l>
                  <l>Kept by thy hand which all things here did found.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="12">12 Sore paines which paſſe the hayres vpon my head,</l>
                  <l>Vexe me on all ſides, which the ſharpeſt ſight</l>
                  <l>Cannot ſo ſoone diſcry: My mind halfe dead,</l>
                  <l>And ſtupid growne, with cares is burn'd vp quite:</l>
                  <l n="13">13 Worlds ſacred Founder, come, giue preſent aid,</l>
                  <l>And draw me out with vtmoſt ills o're-laid.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="14">14 That of their plots aſham'd may lewd men be,</l>
                  <l>Let them heart-breaking Infamy attend,</l>
                  <l>And who layes ſnares to haue intrapped me,</l>
                  <l>Let all their drifts come to a ſhamefull end,</l>
                  <l n="15">15 And taking pleaſure in my ſad diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Be this the harueſt of their wickedneſſe,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:150662:51"/>
                  <l>That they themſelues into the ſnares may fall</l>
                  <l>Which ſtily they had laid to catch me in,</l>
                  <l>And let them fruſtrate ſee their ends in all,</l>
                  <l>Be ſhame their crop, ſince what they ſow'd was ſin.</l>
                  <l>And bluſh he ſtill, and alwaies let him grieue,</l>
                  <l>Who with my teares fed fat laughes in his ſleeue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="16">16 But who commend them wholly to thy grace,</l>
                  <l>Let hope of help refreſh their drooping limmes,</l>
                  <l>And let them alwaies, and in eu'ry place</l>
                  <l>Extoll IEHOVAHS louely name with Hymnes.</l>
                  <l n="17">17 Though hopeleſſe, poore, and comfortleſſe I be,</l>
                  <l>Who guards all things he made wards ouer me.</l>
                  <l>The keeper of my life, and ſureſt ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Come, vexe me not with too too long delay.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="ode">
               <head>PSAL. XLI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BLeſt is the man commiſerates the poore,</l>
                  <l>And brings him helpe when hope begins to die,</l>
                  <l>And when he finds him trampled on the floore,</l>
                  <l>Scoules not at him with a diſdainfull eie.</l>
                  <l>Whom men would think to be in peeces rent,</l>
                  <l>Him God will reare, and cheare him wholly ſpent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="2">2 With faithfull care God will him fence about,</l>
                  <l>And ſet him free from harmes, that ſafe and ſound</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the liuing here enioy he mought</l>
                  <l>A bleſſed life where all contents abound,</l>
                  <l n="3">3 When on his couch griefe layes his aking head,</l>
                  <l>He helpe him then, and makes his eaſefull bed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And all his griefe that pain'd him ſo before,</l>
                  <l n="4">4 He turnes to ſweet repoſe, So when decaid</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:150662:51"/>With bitter <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> was full ſore,</l>
                  <l>Of thee, O God, I crau'd reliefe, and ſaid</l>
                  <l>My wounded ſoule of that foule ſore recure,</l>
                  <l>Which ſinne hath made ſo lothſome to endure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">5 My foe with direfull imprecations ſends</l>
                  <l>Me to the pit of hell, and in my loſſe</l>
                  <l>He triumph makes. And thus he ſaith, When ends</l>
                  <l>That lothed life of his? When ſhall that droſſe</l>
                  <l>Of his impurer carkaſſe in one night,</l>
                  <l>Together with his name be put out quite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="6">6 And if by chance one of this crue eſpie</l>
                  <l>Me drooping goe in body or in mind,</l>
                  <l>He faines as if he mourn'd in paſſing by,</l>
                  <l>And ſighes, forſooth, after a ſporting kind.</l>
                  <l>When going on, and that his backe's but turn'd,</l>
                  <l>He ſpits his gall, that in his boſome burn'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="7">7 The wicked crue conſpiring againſt me,</l>
                  <l>Whiſper in one anothers eare their ſpite,</l>
                  <l>And cloſely plot their miſchiefes, and agree</l>
                  <l>To ioyne in one, and ouer-beare me quite:</l>
                  <l n="8">8 And boaſt that heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſent this dire plague to grieue</l>
                  <l>And bound me with his bonds, nor will relieue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He lyes, ſay they, deiected in his bed</l>
                  <l>Breathing his laſt breath in his latter night.</l>
                  <l n="9">9 But he, in houſe, at board, who dwelt, and fed,</l>
                  <l>My Mate with whom my life I thought I might</l>
                  <l>And liuelihood haue left in ſureſt guard,</l>
                  <l>Euen he, as fierce and fell as who moſt dar'd,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He taking part with my proud foes, did ſpurne</l>
                  <l n="10">
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:150662:52"/>10 And kicke at me. But thou <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> doth giue</l>
                  <l>Me helpe and health, and all baſe ſpite didſt turne</l>
                  <l>Vnto my good, that I might ſweetly liue,</l>
                  <l>Thine eye of grace, and hand of help, Lord, tender,</l>
                  <l>That to my foes I like for like may render.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="11">11 This of thy grace the ſureſt pledge ſhall be,</l>
                  <l>And of thy conſtant purpoſe in mine aid,</l>
                  <l>When as my foe, ſhall not triumph o're me,</l>
                  <l>And though he ſtorme his courage ſhall be laid.</l>
                  <l n="12">12 My body now his former ſtrength retaines,</l>
                  <l>My innocence ſtill in my mind remaines.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And all proceeds from this, that thou thy hand</l>
                  <l>Extend'ſt to me, who took'ſt me to thy charge,</l>
                  <l>That I might ſafe by thy protection ſtand,</l>
                  <l>And alwaies fenc'd. Now ſet by thee at large,</l>
                  <l n="13">13 Thee let the world acknowledge and adore,</l>
                  <l>(Whom <hi>Iſa'chs</hi> race doth ſerue, and no gods more)</l>
                  <l>And let them ſing thy praiſe while day and night</l>
                  <l>Betwixt them ſhare the darkneſſe and the light.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:150662:52"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
